<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second generall epistle to all the saints wherein is unfolded the covenant of grace, as its a law in the spirit, of light, liberty, righteousness, holinesse, power and glory : as likewise as it is a law of peace, love and edification : published for the good of those who love peace and holinesse / written by T. Collier.</title>
            <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12986</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12538735</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12538735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 660:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second generall epistle to all the saints wherein is unfolded the covenant of grace, as its a law in the spirit, of light, liberty, righteousness, holinesse, power and glory : as likewise as it is a law of peace, love and edification : published for the good of those who love peace and holinesse / written by T. Collier.</title>
                  <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 118.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenant theology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Second generall Epiſtle</hi> TO ALL THE SAINTS. Wherein is unfolded the Covenant of grace, as its a Law in the ſpirit, of light, liberty, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glory. As likewiſe as it is a Law of peace, love and edification. <hi>Publiſhed for the good of thoſe who love peace and holineſſe.</hi> Written by <hi>T. Collier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black <hi>Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> neare <hi>Ludgate,</hi> M. DC. XLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:2"/>
            <head>A Preface to the enſuing Epiſtle.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Chriſtian,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE occaſion of my preſenting this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, at preſent, was principally a ſenſibleneſſe of the great miſcarriages that I ſee daily, not onely amongſt the carnall and prophane ones of the world; but many amongſt thoſe who have ſeemingly been purged from their former filthineſſe, yet ſeeme to be returning, if not returned, <hi>with the dogge to his vomit, and the ſow that was waſhed, to their wallowing again</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62920:3"/> 
               <hi>in the mire:</hi> This being a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that befals not onely, a <hi>Judas,</hi> a <hi>Demas,</hi> but ſometimes meets with <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe, with true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, it being covered over with a pretence of holineſſe. I could not at preſent be altogether ſilent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this thing; not that my writing can in any caſe prevent your miſcarriages, its the <hi>anointing in you that muſt and will teach you all things;</hi> but if the ſame anointing ſpeaking in and through me, ſpeak in and to you, it may be through the power of the ſame anointing ſpeaking in both, eſtabliſh and confirme us both in the ſame truth.</p>
            <p>The ſubject I have treated on, and at preſent commend to your conſideration, is the Covenant of grace, that law in the ſpirit which God promiſed in the Prophets, and now makes good in the Saints, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the knowledge of this in
<pb facs="tcp:62920:3"/> power is that will keepe Saints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right with God, prevent them run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into thoſe extravagancies and unheard of opinions and practices, which men, pretending <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> runne into now adaies; there is no law but this law that I know, can deliver ſouls from this <hi>danger;</hi> for prevention of miſtakes, or <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſuring,</hi> I deſire you to obſerve theſe <hi>enſuing rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Without partiality, or a heart biaſſed to any ſide, dealing faithfully with your owne ſoules, looke to God, ſee if he ſpeakes not the ſame truth in you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When I mention ſo often the law in the ſpirit, I minde by it onely the <hi>Covenant of grace, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is all for, and in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The reaſon why I ſo oft mind the falſhood and deluſions of natural &amp; carnal ones as well as of <hi>thoſe</hi> who are or would be <hi>accounted</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62920:4"/> more then ordinary Chriſtians, is becauſe I intend the generall good, my ſoule earneſtly <hi>longing,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after a ſtedfaſtneſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveableneſſe in thoſe who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come in, but likewiſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly <hi>longing</hi> after the <hi>coming</hi> in of more to the knowledge of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which is a ſoul-converting, eſtabliſhing and glorifying Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In what reſpect may Christ be ſaid to be the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace as he was given forth by the Father, therein to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate and declare grace; <hi>The Father to make forth that fulneſſe of grace that was and is in himſelfe for ſinners, gives forth his Sonne as the Covenant; There is my Sonne, my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved, take him for a Covenant, that your ſoules may be ſatisfied in the knowledge of my grace, Iſa.</hi> 42. 6.
<pb facs="tcp:62920:4"/> 
               <hi>I will give the for a Covenant to the people, for a light to the Gentiles:</hi> He is called <hi>the miniſter or meſſenger of the Covenant, Mal.</hi> 3. 1. Becauſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by him and through him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares this <hi>grace</hi> unto the ſonnes of men, and communicates his to whom he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>2. As the Father thus gives forth Chriſt a Covenant, in whom he declares <hi>grace,</hi> doing all in him, for us, without us, ſo he comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſoules by the ſame ſpirit that he was in Chriſt; ſo that Chriſt comes not onely as a Covenant to us, but in us, and the ſame law of ſpirit and life takes poſſeſſion of us; and this is the law <hi>written in the heart,</hi> which will occaſion ſoules in whom it is, never to depart from God.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why is this Covenant called a new Covenant, is it not the ſame that was in the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Its true thoſe that were ſaved, were ſaved in and by the ſame Covenant.</p>
            <p>Yet, 2. This Covenant, to ſpeake in the <hi>language</hi> of Scripture, was not then made, but the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant then made verbally, in word, was another Covenant, and that of workes, which was broken. Now becauſe this ſeemes to be a doubt and ſcruple, I ſhall give you ſeverall cleare demonſtrations for the confirmation of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Scripture cals it, <hi>Two Covenants,</hi> an old and a new, <hi>I will make a new Covenant, not ſuch a Covenant as I made with your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c. Jer.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But ſome will ſay, that its called an old and a new, but therein to declare the clearneſſe of grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell, yet the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as there is the old and new Moone, when all is but one and the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is not called a new Covenant in reſpect of the clearneſſe, but in reſpect of the nature of it; its not the ſame, <hi>I will make a Covenant, but not ſuch a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as I made with your Fathers:</hi> The difference of the nature of theſe Covenants will appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That was a Covenant written and engraven in <hi>Tables of ſtone,</hi> this is a Covenant written and engraven in the heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That was a Covenant that could not give life nor cauſe to walke, <hi>becauſe of its weakneſſe, Heb.</hi> 7. 18. But this Covenant is a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That was a Covenant that directly <hi>tended to bondage, Gal.</hi> 4. 23, 24. But this unto grace and ſpirituall liberty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Covenant was but a type, a ſhadow, this the ſubſtance, therefore not the ſame, no more
<pb facs="tcp:62920:6"/> then the Jewiſh Ordinances, who were all typicall and ſhadowes, was the ſubſtance or thing ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; no more the ſame then thoſe creatures ſacrificed was Chriſt; no more then the bloud <hi>of the Paſchall Lamb ſprinkled on the door posts,</hi> was the bloud of Chriſt; or the <hi>land of Canaan</hi> the ſpirituall reſt of Chriſtians; but all was typicall, and the ſubſtance was ſhadowed forth in thoſe types, and Saints found grace couched under this old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: The miſtake of this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions much miſcarriage amongſt many, looking upon the Covenant to be the ſame now as formerly, wil have a Covenant without now as then; and hence ſet up fleſhly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of their owne invention, ſutable to ſuch a Covenant, by which thouſands are deluded; whereas the truth is, that then there was a Covenant in the fleſh which <hi>gendred to bondage,</hi> which onely
<pb facs="tcp:62920:6"/> thoſe in the ſpirit were delivered from, by the myſtery couched un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Covenant, which none af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh could ſee into; but we are onely under this Covenant in the ſpirit, which is a Covenant of liberty, a Covenant of grace and much glory, and none are owned in this Covenant, but thoſe who are in it, that is, thoſe in whoſe hearts it is written. Its true, men may be in the profeſſion of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant who are not in it, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew it, but they ought not to be there; and there ſhall not a man paſſe for currant, that hath not on <hi>this wedding garment; with, Friend, how camest thou in hither? take him and binde him hand and foot, caſt him into utter darkneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Thus this Covenant being rightly knowne, we ſhall be able to ſee and ſay, that its a Covenant of grace indeed, a Covenant of peace and love indeed, in which our ſouls
<pb facs="tcp:62920:7"/> ſhall be abundantly refreſhed, and powerfully upheld in and under all temptations and conditions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That was a Covenant that might be broken, <hi>that was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Jer.</hi> 31. this a Covenant that ſhall never be broken, its an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant poſſeſſing ſoules <hi>with everlaſting grace and love, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy and praiſes, Iſa.</hi> 35. laſt. This Covenant in the ſpirit is the everlaſting, never-erring light and rule of Saints experienced; it is that anointing which teacheth all things; and ſo I commend it to you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. OF the light of the Law in the ſpirit.</item>
               <item>2. Of nine falſe lights flowing from the Law in the fleſh.</item>
               <item>3. Of the liberty of the Law in the ſpirit.</item>
               <item>4. Of falſe Liberty.</item>
               <item>5. Of the righteouſneſſe of the Law in the ſpirit.</item>
               <item>6. Of the unrighteous Law.</item>
               <item>7. Of the Law of true holineſſe.</item>
               <item>8. Of falſe or fleſhly holineſſe.</item>
               <item>9. Of the power of the Law in the ſpirit.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62920:8"/>
               <item>10. Of the power of this Law in the fleſh.</item>
               <item>11. Of the glory of this Law in the ſpirit.</item>
               <item>12. Of the Law in the ſpirit, a Law of peace.</item>
               <item>13. As it is likewiſe a Law of peace.</item>
               <item>14. Of the Law of Love.</item>
               <item>15. Its a Law of Edification.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62920:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Second</hi> GENERALL EPISTLE To all the Saints.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. I. Shewing the Light of the Law in the Spirit.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is light, and in him there is no darkneſſe at all:</hi> All though its true, God is with his People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>dark diſpenſations,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them in it, though many times they are ignorant
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62920:9"/> of it; and although it's true, ſoules once gathered up, by the power of light; into its own fulneſſe, where it beholds the purity, ſweetneſſe, and glory of the inviſible God; being in ſome meaſure, through that fight, made conformable unto him, and partaker of that ſelfe ſame glory; the diſcovery of true light in Saints, being the right way of true enjoyment.</p>
               <p>Now Saints when they have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drunk of the bitter cup with Chriſt, <hi>(viz.) The cup of ſufferings,</hi> and ſo have been made <hi>conformable to him in his death;</hi> but likewiſe have drunk new wine with him <hi>in his Fathers Kingdome,</hi> even that wine of the Spirit, <hi>which makes glad the heart of the City of God;</hi> hence the ſoul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus imbrac'd into the boſome of love, and at preſent come in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his dear Son, concludes with the Prophet, <hi>Thou haſt made my mountain ſo ſtrong I ſhall never be moved;</hi> but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly the Father withholding thoſe manifeſtations and ſweet imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the boſome of Love, the ſoule is troubled; <hi>Thou didſt but hide thy face, and I was troubled:</hi> This was <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, who was <hi>caught up into the third heaven,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62920:9"/> 
                  <hi>ſaw and heard things unutterable,</hi> yet the Father lets him down again under a cloud of fleſh; which ſeems at preſent to eclipſe and darken his former glory, which was his trouble and his burthen, deſiring to be rid of it; but he was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> my ſtrength ſhall be perfected in thy weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; this being the experienced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of many a precious ſoul who, although they are ſometimes taken up into the <hi>third heavens,</hi> and ſo have a taſt given them of the heavenly glory, yet they are let down again under a cloud of fleſh living upon grace, looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and haſting unto the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of the great God; knowing, <hi>That when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, wee ſhall appear with him in Glory;</hi> that as wee ſuffer with him, wee ſhall raign with him.</p>
               <p>Now there being falſe Light, which is indeed darknes it felfe, in the world, and a myſtery of iniquity under the pretence of truth, by which many are deceived: I ſhall therefore in this inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe, according to the meaſure received, give a brief touch of the true Light, Liberty, Righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62920:10"/> Holines, Power and Glory of the Law in the Spirit, the Covenant of grace written in the heart, in oppoſition too and diſcovering of that law of darknes, ſin and fleſh, the one being the law of the new, the other the Law of the old man.</p>
               <p>This Law in the Spirit, is the Spirit it ſelfe conforming ſouls to it ſelfe; and its firſt a Spirit, a law of light, even that true light, that lighteth every ſoule <hi>that comes to the Father; He is light, and in him there is no darkneſſe at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Law of light, where it works powerfully, where it works ſavingly, it enlightens the underſtanding, in theſe ten particulars following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It enlightneth the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by which it comes to ſee the evill of ſinne, the evil nature of it, the evill conſequences of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The evil nature of it, the evill fountain from whence it flowes, even the fountain of fleſh and devil, a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and filthy root, which produceth fruit ſutable unto ſuch a tree, which is Death, the conſequent or fruit of ſinne, <hi>The wages of ſinne is death;</hi> the ſoul is now taught to ſee the evil nature of ſin, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62920:10"/> contrariety of it unto the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the ſoul can ſee and ſay truly, that although ſinne is nothing to God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſin reacheth not God, yet it is abſolutely contrary to thoſe divine and heavenly diſcoveries of <hi>God</hi> made forth in the ſpirits of Chriſtians; if you ſearch the Scripture you ſhall finde this a manifeſt truth in the Spirits working; See <hi>Act. 2. 37. chap,</hi> 9. 3, 4, 5, 6. If you ſearch your own experience, you ſhall finde it ſutable; never any ſoule made partaker of grace, but firſt made ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the want of grace, by the enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power of the Spirit of grace in the diſcovery of a mans ſelfe unto himſelf, and ſo of the evill nature, of the evill conſequence of ſin, which is a ſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an internal and ſpirituall death under darkneſſe, and a lake of fire; and this worke of diſcovery by this Law of light is effected, not only in ſoules at their firſt converſion; but all along while fleſh and ſinne remains, <hi>till death is ſwallowed up in life, and mortality hath put on immortality, till Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, then ſhall we appear with him in glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Que. <hi>What is ſinne?</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62920:11"/> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sinne, is a tranſgreſſion of, or turning aſide from a righteous Law; if wee judge of ſinne by a letter, a law without us, then it is a tranſgreſſion of that Law, a turning aſide from the Law; but if we judge of ſin according to the light of the Law in the Spirit, then all turnings aſide from, all motions and actings contrary unto that Spirit of life and light, are ſinne; and indeed ſouls living in the light of this law are able to judge between the motions and actings of fleſh and ſpirit, they are made able to judge truly of good and evill, and that not by eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, but by being made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the fruit of the Tree of Life.</p>
               <p>So that now the Chriſtians diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſinne is not ſo much after the law of the old, as after the law of the new man, that law <hi>of ſpirit and life in Chriſt,</hi> which is a ſinne diſcovering law where it enlightens; ſo that a Chriſtian in the light of this law, ſces every motion to evill, every luſt and corruption, the whole body of fleſh, to be contrary to that divine &amp; ſpirituall law, to that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62920:11"/> nature received; and hence is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a continuall warre againſt it, untill that <hi>warfare be accompliſhed</hi> in the ending of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This law in the Spirit is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a light diſcovering ſinne, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a light diſcovering <hi>Love</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from ſinne.</p>
               <p>Firſt it diſcovers <hi>Love</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Creatures ſinne; nay, not only ſo, but it is <hi>Love</hi> in that Law that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſinne, and it ſelfe, who is <hi>Love</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Creatures while they ſinne; herein is the riches and freeneſſe of grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded in the diſcovery of Love and grace unto Creatures, who are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unlovely; he opens a fountain of <hi>Love,</hi> notwithſtanding ſinne; a fountain of blood and Spirit to waſh away both the guilt and power of ſinne, a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living waters, even thoſe waters of life, that revives and comforts the weary ſoule in a barren and dry land; thus this Spirit of light, leads poor, empty, hungring and longing ſoules out of a barren and dry land, that land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> a land of blackneſſe and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of oppreſſion and hardſhip, through and out of the wilderneſſe and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62920:12"/> ſolitary condition into the ſweet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements of the Fathers <hi>Love,</hi> both into the freeneſſe and fulneſſe of it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Creatures ſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of its own unworthineſſe, and now the ſoul being thus lighted to, and poſſeſſed with this everlaſting <hi>Love</hi> and grace; it is likewiſe brought in ſight of a lovely &amp; gracious deliverance, a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from the <hi>guilt,</hi> a <hi>deliverance</hi> from the power of the Law in fleſh; that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Chriſtian, through the powerfull working of corruption can ſay, many times with the Apoſtle, <hi>Ob wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of ſinne?</hi> Yet it can ſay, by faith triumphingly, <hi>Thanks be unto God who giveth a victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> fleſh oft-times acts in Saints for their tryall; and they are to paſſe through <hi>many tribulations</hi> to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; through a Sea of Glaſſe mingled with fire; yet in concluſion they ſhall ſtand on top or above them all (with the harps of God in their hands) the Spirit making ſweet melody in their hearts ſinging the ſong of <hi>Moſes, Praiſe be to him that ſitteth upon the Throne and to the Lamb for ever;</hi> thus this Law of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62920:12"/> Spirit in righteous ſouls, not only of ſinne and miſery, but likewiſe of love and deliverance; it leads the ſoule not only into the beholding of darkneſſe and ſorrow; but it leads the ſoule out again into the beholding of light, love and deliverance; and ſo it ſhall be truly ſaid of them, <hi>Theſe are they that are come out of great tribulation, and have waſhed themſelves white in the blood of the Lamb;</hi> theſe are they that have gone through many tribulations to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This Law in the Spirit diſcovers not only a <hi>deliverance</hi> from fleſh and ſinne, by which the ſoule is kept below its glory; but it likewiſe diſcovers a glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance into that ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Kingdome, where is nothing leſſe then peace, purity and perfection; it hath an entrance given, into that everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdome <hi>of his dear Sonne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, It hath a light given, by and in which it ſees into that Kingdome; <hi>In thy light we ſee light;</hi> and that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is within us; in this light the ſoul ſees into the ſeverall dimenſions and glory of it; it ſees it to be a Kingdome altogether lovely, altogether delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62920:13"/> of deſire, he ſees it to be a Kingdom of righteouſneſſe, holines, peace, joy, and full of ſpirituall glory; he now ſees that no unclean thing can enter into this Kingdome; all fleſh and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, all hypocrites and hypocriſy, all things that love and make a lye muſt be without, <hi>caſt out into utter darkneſſe where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, As there is a ſight, ſo there is an entring into that everlaſting Kingdome, with a full expectation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure ground of being eternally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in that Kingdome; hence it is the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Pſalm 145. 10, 11, 12. Thy Saints ſhall bleſſe thee, they ſhall ſpeake of the glory of thy Kingdome, and talke of thy power, to make known to men his mighty acts and the glorious majeſty of his Kingdome;</hi> marke you here, the Saints ſhall ſpeake of the majeſty of his Kingdome, and ſhall make known the glory of it to the ſons of men, and why ſo? Becauſe they are a ble to give a true relation of it; they have been in the Kingdome, and can ſpeak experimentally of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: note by the way, who are the likelieſt men to make known the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God to others, Univerſity
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62920:13"/> men, or Saints; the Scripture ſaith, the Saints ſhall doe it, for to them it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to know the myſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; they have been in the Kingdome, others parhaps have heard of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſo can ſpeak ſomthing by hear-ſay; but the Saints they have been in the Kingdome, and the Kingdome in them, and they can ſpeake experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally of the grace and peace of it, and of the glory of it too in a meaſure; a wonderfull deluſion, that poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant creatures ſhould imagine that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane arts, the wiſdome of the fleſh, ſhould be able to unfold the Kingdome of God unto them, or to preach the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Goſpel, which is called the word of the Kingdome; no, no, it's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Saints onely to doe it, who alone have by the light of this Law in the Spirit, been delivered into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of righteouſnes peace, and joy; others may ſpeak and talke rudely of it, but alas they know not what it is, they never did ſo much as ſee into the <hi>glory</hi> of it, never had ſo much as a pee-phole opened to ſee one glimpſe of that light, of that grace, of that <hi>glory; John 3. 3. Except a man be born from above.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62920:14"/> he cannot ſo much as ſee into the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of God; but Saints are delivered into this <hi>Kingdome</hi> in a meaſure by this law in the Spirit: beloved it's the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of this light of God, to gather up ſouls into it ſelfe: The Kingdome of Heaven is a Kingdome of <hi>light,</hi> and in the <hi>light</hi> of Heaven, which is God, who is light, we ſhall ſee light and enjoy that light: the light of this Law is a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming light, <hi>I</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>am come a light into the world, he that believeth on me ſhall not abide in darkneſſe, John 12. 46. and we all with one face beholding as in a glaſſe, the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image,</hi> or likeneſſe: <hi>that as we have borne the image of the earthly, ſo now we ſhall bear the image of the heavenly, being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of that Kingdome of darkneſſe, into the Kingdome of his dear Son,</hi> which is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of light, light being ſown for the righteous, and gladnes <hi>for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Souls delivered into, or partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of this law of light, are able in this light to judge of things that differ; Light is that which makes true diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of things in their colours; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe either wholly hides the appearance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62920:14"/> of a thing, or elſe preſents it at the beſt as in a falſe glaſſe; but <hi>light</hi> is that which makes all things manifeſt; ſo this light in the Spirit, expels that darknes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by which the underſtanding was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wholly blinded, or elſe had things preſented in another ſhape then what they are in themſelves; but now the new man in this light is able to judge according to the meaſure of light recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; it now no longer cals evil good, and good evil; it puts not light for darknes, and darknes for light; it cals not every thing good, though it ſees God working good out of every things, it ſees and is able to ſay, that <hi>that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh, and that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit,</hi> it juſtifieth not the wicked thing, nor taketh away the righteouſneſſe of the righteous from him; in a word, the ſoul in whom this glorious light of God is manifeſt, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a meaſure, to judge between fleſh and ſpirit, fancy and reality, ſhadow and ſubſtance, form and power, notions and true diſcoveries, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions and true enjoyments; <hi>The SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALL MAN judgeth all things, yet hee himſelfe is judged of no man:</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62920:15"/> that is according to the meaſure of <hi>light</hi> received he judgeth; not but that it is poſſible for a ſpirituall man, who is in part renewed, to be under a temptation; a cloude of darknes for a time, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Sun be there, yet that dark and black cloude prevents the ſhining of it, <hi>But unto you that fear my name ſhall the Sun of righteouſneſſe ariſe with healing in his wings;</hi> the winde of the Spirit ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe thoſe clouds and miſts, of thick darkneſſe, and the glorious light ſhall again appear, to the chearing and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting of the weary ſoul, cauſing the ſhadowes to fly away <hi>in his holy mountain,</hi> and then the ſoul comes againe clearly to ſee wherein it was miſtaken, and then he can ſay with the Prophet, ſo fooliſh was I and ignorant, <hi>I was even a beaſt before thee:</hi> thus <hi>light</hi> appearing they no more juſtify fleſh and darkneſſe, but juſtify God in every thing; they no more lay their temptations to luſt and fleſhlyneſſe, upon God, but upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; having a true diſcovery made within themſelves by the light of this Law of the righteouſnes, holines, and glory of the Father, they cannot but cry out, <hi>Holy, holy, holy Lord God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62920:15"/> 
                  <hi>Heaven and Earth is filled with thy glory;</hi> and now they are abaſed with <hi>Jobe, I have heard of thee by the hearing of the eare, but now mine eyes have ſeen thee, wherefore I abhorre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes:</hi> Oh, my beloved ones, when once the ſoul hath ſeen the Lord, then it laies downe the juſtification of fleſh, then, and never till then, it truly, it ſavingly abhors it ſelf, layeth it ſelf low, and the Lord alone is exalted in that ſoul: when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſayah</hi> had ſeen the Lord, Chap. 6. Then, <hi>Wo is me, I am undone, I am a man of poluted lips, for mine eyes have ſeen the King, even the Lord of hoſts;</hi> this glorious and pure viſion of the Almighty within us, will be not only a light diſcovering, but a fire burning up all things below and contrary to it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This <hi>Light</hi> of the Spirit cauſeth the ſoul to ſee more excellency in God in Heaven, in ſpirituall things, then in all other things in the world beſides; nay, it now ſees all other things below to be but dung and droſſe in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of of Chriſt; when men of the earth are taken up with earthly excellencies, this ſoul can ſay, Lord <hi>lift up the light of thy countenance upon me,</hi> that'<hi>s light</hi> will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62920:16"/> fill me with more joy, <hi>then thoſe whoſe corne and wine and oyle abounds;</hi> the ſoule ſees a goodnes, a lovelines in God, in Chriſt, in the Spirit, by way of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; it doth not only ſay that God is good, but he is moſt good, <hi>his love is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then wine,</hi> better then life; his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance cauſeth more joy then corn and wine and oyle; Oh this is ſweet, when experimentally enjoyed! then the ſoule can ſay, <hi>Thy word is ſweet unto my mouth, yea, ſweeter then hony</hi> to my taſt, <hi>ſweeter then hony and the hony comb,</hi> better <hi>then thouſands of gold and ſilver;</hi> now the ſoule eyes to worldly and fleſhly excellencies, as it is gathered up more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious excellency of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; it hath a propriety in God by way of excellency, and hence it comes to paſs that no propriety below this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, is of any value to a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a changed minde.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This Law of light, cauſeth thoſe, inwhom it is according the meaſure of its manifeſtation, to ſee God in every thing, to ſee him and enjoy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him in all conditions, and this is a ſweet diſcovery, a heavenly light, which produceth a heavenly life; when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62920:16"/> 
                  <hi>the ſoul ſees &amp; enjoyes God in all things; when it ſees God to lye, as it were, at the bottom of every creature, of every mercy, ſees him to be the life, the fountain, the glory of all; ſtreaming light, love &amp; communion to the ſoul through al: now it can ſay, God is to me the life, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the excellency of creatures, by which I live, and ſo I live not by bread only, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God; it ſees a ſtream of life and power from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the uſe of them; it now in that light, ſees God in wicked mens actings to them, ſees him in every diſpenſation, whether more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or more frowning, to a fleſhly apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether it be in proſperity or adverſity, in priſon or liberty, poverty or riches, in light or darknes, it can ſay truly, God is good to Iſrael, to ſuch as are upright in heart; &amp; all things ſhal work together for good to ſuch as love God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This Law of light, cauſeth the ſoul not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſee God in all things; but it preſents matter of rejoycing in all conditions; ſouls thus enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, can ſing in priſon, enjoying communion with God; there they can ſee it to be good, being where their Father will have them to be; much more where they enjoy the preſence of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſting love &amp; grace to them &amp; in them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. They living in this light, ſeeing al conditions to be good, through the appearance of the good God in it, can now ſee and ſay, thar it's not the leaſt part of their happineſſe while they are here, to live fully and compleatly in the will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62920:17"/> of their Father; Oh, ſaith the ſoul, that I could attain to this, but to live ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and contentedly in the will of God, what a tranſcendent excellency doth the enlightned ſoul ſee in this one thing! how would this quiet and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all fleſhly and carnall riſings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlikings, and quarrelings againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence; it can ſay, Good is the Word of the Lord, and <hi>good is the will of the Lord,</hi> and good is this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me, becauſe its my Fathers good pleaſure ſo to have it, who knows beſt what is good for me; an excellent diſcovery, but more excellent, when li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the power, in the glory of it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This Law of light diſcovers the vanity and folly of all fleſhly wiſdome in the things of God; this Law of light makes that ſoul truly ſenſible in whom its manifeſt, of the difference betweene the wiſdome of the firſt and ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and ſo that word is fulfilled in him; if any man will be wiſe, let him be a fool that he may be wiſe; he ſhall be a fool (that is) made truly ſenſible of the folly of all fleſhly wiſdome; the inſufficiency of the light of nature and wiſdome of the fleſh to attain the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62920:17"/> knowledge of God, or the things of God, <hi>For in him are hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge,</hi> and its a gift of the Spirit, to thoſe whoſe eyes are enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſee into this myſtery; <hi>To you its given to know the myſtery,</hi> or ſecrets; <hi>of the Kingdome,</hi> when its hid from others; they are ſtrangers to it, though never ſo much indued with fleſhly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And finally, This Law of life <hi>is a light and lamp unto the feet</hi> and paths of thoſe in whom its manifeſt, to lead and direct them into its waies; it is that voyce behind them ſaying, <hi>This is the way walke in it;</hi> when they turn to the right or left hand, it's that light which guides them into all their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings whether civil or ſpirituall; it is their great comforter, without whoſe direction they cannot comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably act in any of their undertakings; in a word, it's that Spirit of light and life that occaſions motion &amp; action ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to its owne nature, and ſets the ſoule upon that worke which is higher then it ſelfe; that way which is a way of light and truth.</p>
               <p>Thus the Law in the Spirit, is a Law
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62920:18"/> of light, giving underſtanding unto the ſimple, enlightning the minde, it is the true light that lighteneth the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of every Sunne and daughter of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. II. Shewing nine falſe Lights, flowing from the Law in the fleſh.</head>
               <p>BUT there is a falſe Light, as well as a true Light; there is a Law in the fleſh, as well as in the Spirit; although its true that all falſe Light is indeed darknes, though men call it light, <hi>If the light that is in thee be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe!</hi> therefore I ſhal ſpeak ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by way of diſcovery of this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, this power of darkneſſe, under the nominall tearme of light; this falſe Chriſt, or rather this Antichriſt; which if it were poſſible, would deceive the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry elect.</p>
               <p>Now this falſe light, or rather delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this law in the fleſh, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under theſe following conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62920:18"/>
                  <head>Firſt falſe light.</head>
                  <p>1. It preſents low, carnall and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellencies unto the creature, as its chiefeſt good; it gives a falſe repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things; it cals evil good, and good evill; it puts light for darknes, and darknes for light; it judgeth ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be bitter, and bitter to be ſweet, and thus it repreſents the worſt things with the greateſt excellency; in more particular.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it diſcovers not ſinne and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motions, and fleſhly actings as the greateſt evil, but as the greateſt good; thus the ſoule is deluded with a falſe light, when it looks upon the deeds of darknes as deeds of pleaſure, and the waies and paths of darknes, to be waies and paths of pleaſantnes and peace, and thus it becomes a pleaſure and paſtime to a fool to commit folly; this is the univerſall ſpirit of Satan, and law of darknes that rules in the world, even in the hearts of the children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; ſo that in a word, the worlds way is a way of darknes, and they delight to have it ſo.</p>
                  <p>Its true, ſometimes they hear of Chriſt and grace by the hearing of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62920:19"/> eare: but the uſe they make of it, through the deceivablenes of this falſe and dark light, is to ſinne the more freely, to give up themſelues to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the fleſh, with the leſs trouble: thus are the moſt, the greateſt part of the world blinded to their own ruine, and yet think they ſee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Second falſe light.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, this Law in the fleſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the world as an excellent thing, as the chiefeſt good to many a ſoul, who will ſhew us any good, ſaith the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creature, who thinks the world beſt; hence it is ſo many, and that under the form and notion of godlines to, hunt ſo earneſtly after worldly honors, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, pleaſures; doe not ſuch through that falſe glaſs that thus repreſents things, apprehend the chiefeſt good, the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt exellency to be in the world; when alas, thoſe poor deluded ſouls ſee no excellency, no preciouſnes in God the fountain, it forſakes him and runs to ſtreams; not but that every creature of God is good, the ſoule beholding and enjoying the good God in it: <hi>but without God there is nothing good, no man good, no creature good, nothing good, God is</hi> the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62920:19"/> of all things unto an enlightened, renewed minde; now this love of the world, and being taken up with, and living in the worlds excellencie, the worlds glory, is, not only the ſinne, and will be the ſhame of men of the earth, who have their portion in this life; but its a temptation that lights many times very heavy upon thoſe who are Chriſtians, Saints indeed; Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſet upon by this temptation; and I believe Chriſtians, who have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience within themſelves of that new birth which is from above, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way of true holineſſe, can bear witnes to this truth; amongſt all their fiery tryalsand temptations this is one, to imbrace <hi>this preſent evil world,</hi> not evil in it ſelfe, but evill to him, who hath an evil <hi>heart to depart from the living God,</hi> making the world its dead Idol; this is that with which the world is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: mad they are in the imbracing the honours, profits, and pleaſures of this preſent world; this is that which overcomes the heart of many a <hi>Judas;</hi> what will ye give me; of many a <hi>Demas,</hi> who after much profeſſion, forſake the Lord, <hi>imbracing this preſent world; be yee</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62920:20"/> therefore watchfull, for your adverſary the <hi>Devil</hi> goeth about night &amp; day, <hi>like a roaring Lion,</hi> ſeeking <hi>who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> he may devour; &amp; one of his greateſt temptations &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions is the preſenting to your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings the glory of this world; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though its true, he falſly repreſents it too, for he preſents it glorious in it ſelfe, to the deceiving of the ſoule, but never preſents God, who is the quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the excellency and the glory of all things, without whom there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing glorious, nothing excellent, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing truly ſatisfactory or lovely; this is the ſecond falſe or deceivable light, preſenting things which are indeed good without him, who is the goodneſſe of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Third falſe light.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, If God make ſome diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſinne to the naturall conſcience, it being convinced of ſin, waded under the apprehenſions of it; this falſe law in the fleſh, the ſpirit of Satan and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if poſſible he can, enſnares the ſoul under one of theſe miſ-preſentations.</p>
                  <p>Either 1. That notwithſtanding there is ſuch a diſcovery made of ſin, yet it is not ſo bad as is preſented at preſent, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62920:20"/> there he preſents the fleſhly ſweetneſſe and pleaſure of it, hurryes on the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into the moſt delightfull motions and actings of it; that ſo by the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pleaſure of ſinne to fleſh, the troubled thoughts of ſinne might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peld.</p>
                  <p>But 2. If this will not doe, the breath of the Lord kindles, not onely new di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcoveries, but fiery flames, then the beſt way is, with <hi>Adam,</hi> to hide himſelfe, if not with <hi>Judas,</hi> to hang it ſelfe; an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely way to be delivered from fiery flames, though many ſoules are thus deluded by that lying ſpirit withinthem.</p>
                  <p>3. But if this will not <hi>prevaile,</hi> then it will ſet the creature on worke, with <hi>Adam,</hi> to make clothes to cover it ſelfe withall, although it be but figge leaves; that is, it will preſent unto the ſoule ſome creature righteouſneſſe and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſome forme of godlineſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power, as light and life enough to deliver the ſoule out of this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it cloths the creature with a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of its owne ſetting up re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations, humiliations, prayers, teares, preaching, hearing in the roome of Chriſt, and the ſpirit; like unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62920:21"/> 
                     <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Judah, Hoſ.</hi> 5. 13. when they ſaw their ſickneſſe, ſinne and wound, then they went to the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> for helpe, but he could not helpe them; and if they are healed, that is falſly and unſoundly cured, it proves their ruine; for they become ſeven times more the children of hel and darkneſſe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: thus this law of fleſh will through its deceivablenes, gather up the ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fleſhly forms, things ſutable to it ſelfe, miſtaking Chriſt and the ſpirit of truth; ſaying, this is Chriſt, thus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelf into an Angel of light, to deceive ſouls; but thoſe who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>riſen with Chriſt,</hi> ſeeke things above, of a higher nature: &amp; if they at any time act in formes, it is not the forme that ſatisfyeth them, but Chriſt who is the ſubſtance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Fourth falſe light.</head>
                  <p>But Fourthly, When the ſoule comes to ſee that there is yet ſomething above all formes and fleſhly grounds of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; When it comes to be truly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or at leaſt to get a notion that there is a law in the ſpirit, an internall, an inviſible law which is indeed the true light and guide of all the Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctings:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62920:21"/> This law in the fleſh, or this ſpirit of darkneſſe, which is Antichriſt, working in the higheſt myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and unrighteouſneſſe, will be here working to the purpoſe too, &amp; he hath here ſeverall deceits under the pretence of light.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, In the throwing downe of all workes of holineſſe and viſible demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of piety, under the pretence of a more ſpirituall enjoyment: Whereas before it lived in theſe, now it throwes off all theſe as a thing of nought, as watchings over and reprovings for ſin, righteous and in-offenſive walkings, love to the brethren, ſpirituall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications of what the ſoule enjoyes, meekneſſe, patience, prayer, &amp;c. which are all fruits of the ſpirit: this is now all deſtroyed as a thing of nought, by this law in the fleſh; and this falſe light is that with which the Saints themſelves are ſometimes tempted: but the light of God, the law in the ſpirit, diſcovers it and expels it, and it lets the ſoule to ſee that holineſſe is becoming the Houſe of the Lord for ever.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, This ſpirit of deluſion workes the minde into an earthly, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62920:22"/> diſtempered temper, filling it with pride, high-conceitedneſſe of its owne excellency, paſſion and peeviſhneſſe of ſpirit, carnall and earthly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with a contentedneſſe in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, becauſe the creature is informed, that its ſutable to this high diſcovery of God, which is indeed but a falſe ſuggeſtion of the ſpirit of deluſion; to this purpoſe <hi>James</hi> minds this excellent word, <hi>James 3. 14. But if yee have bitter envyings and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, lye not againſt the truth.</hi> This wiſedome comes not from above, but is earthly, ſenſuall and deviliſh; that wiſedome which leades men into a ſpirituall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalneſſe, looſeneſſe and liberty, into pride, paſſion and peeviſhneſſe, is not from above, but from the bottomleſſe pit: this likewiſe fils the converſation with an externall appearance of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vanity, unprofitableneſſe and pride, ſleighting all others who are not in the ſame temper with them.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, This ſpirit of deluſion, this myſtery of iniquity, never leaves, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he can accompliſh it, till he works the poore creature to and into its firſt ſtation, not onely to the owning in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62920:22"/> judgement, but to the practiſe of all looſeneſſe and licenciouſneſſe, and that too under pretence of being taught by the ſpirit: the ſpirit it is indeed, but its the ſpirit of darkneſſe and not of light. Now the ſoule comes, as it ſaith, in this darke and deſtroying light, to ſee that all things are alike to God, that there is no ſinne, but all actings are Gods, or in his power, therefore all is good. There now in the eſteem of ſuch, to lye, ſteale, be drunke, commit adultery, and the like, is all good to ſuch a creature, and that God is now throwing his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of all formes of righteouſneſſe, as well as out of formes of worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Thus this man of ſinne working, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, ruining, layes all upon God, and the holy and pure ſpirit muſt beare all the blame and ſhame of this filthy ſpirits working, when the truth is, God can as ſoone throw downe himſelfe, as throw righteouſneſſe and holineſſe out of his people; and this thoſe who are taught of God, in whom the light of the ſpirit is manifeſt, can beare witneſſe unto: although its true, there is none of all theſe temptations, but the Saints have had ſome experience, ſome trials from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62920:23"/> the Prince and power of darkneſſe, by which means they are the better enabled to ſpeake and write in the diſcovery of it.</p>
                  <p>I deny not in any caſe the glorious diſpenſation of that law in the ſpirit; its a more full diſcovery of that law I wait for, that ſo there might be a more full conformity both within and without unto it.</p>
                  <p>Yet it is that I have ſaid often, and muſt now ſpeake it againe, that its ſuch a law, ſuch a diſcovery, as in it all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ones and hypocrites ſhall be left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde in it; the one below it, ſtill op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, living upon ſomething of fleſh; the other in the notion of it only, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beyond it, and ſo <hi>with the dogge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his vomit, and the ſow that was waſht, to her wallowing againe in the mire:</hi> This is indeed the narrow and ſtrait gate and way of life, few there be that finde it.</p>
                  <p>But ſome perhaps may hereby object, and ſay; <hi>Sir, What you ſay ſeemes to ſavour of the fleſh, of a low, darkened and enſlaved ſpirit, and is indeed Barbariſme to a ſoule: In lightneſſe we know that all things are good, and that which you call ſinne is good, and all moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62920:23"/> 
                     <hi>and workes are alike good: from whence comes ſin? doth not it come from God? is there any power beſides God, or that which is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him? and therefore are not all things and actions alike good?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, Firſt, It is true, there is no power but is of God, yet there are thoſe who in that power act things which the Moſt High hath ſentenced with death; and not only the things, but thoſe who practiſe them: &amp; that not only in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; where we finde this truth in the Saints experience; <hi>I proteſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, by my rejoycing in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord I dye daily;</hi> and this ſpirituall death, which many are ignorant of, was, and is one great part of the myſtery of the Croſſe of Chriſt within us: this likewiſe is the experience of thoſe who live in light; they have received the ſentence of death within them; I meane, the death of ſin and fleſh; and for this they waite till it be accompliſhed.</p>
                  <p>Againe, although all things had their firſt riſe and being from him, and ſtill ſubſiſt by him, yet the corruption of thoſe things flowes from it ſelf, and not from him: and beſides, God hath ſet up two creations, two <hi>Adams,</hi> the one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62920:24"/> after the fleſh, the other after the ſpirit; the one being but a figure of the other; <hi>the one is of the earth, earthly; the ſecond is the Lord from heaven;</hi> In the one, to declare himſelfe a juſt God, in ſentencing and condemning all ſinne and fleſh, becauſe in that firſt creation after the fleſh, ſinne and fleſh workes: In the ſecond, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelf not only a God ſentencing ſinne and fleſh, but likewiſe a God of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſſe; ſuch a one with whom the throne of iniquity can have no fellowſhip: and this I am ſure is the Saints experience; nothing eclypſes the glorious enjoyment but wars and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings within them from luſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What need we make ſo much of ſinne? God is good, and be ſeeth no iniquity in his people?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Its true, God ſeeth, that is, ſuffereth no travell againſt, nor iniquity in his people to hurt them, to ſeparate them from him: but it is as true, that thoſe who have this teſtimony within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, cannot ſee ſin and fleſh working in themſelves with delight and pleaſure; <hi>Shall we ſinne becauſe grace abounds? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid!</hi> How ſhall we, who are dead to ſin, continue any longer therein?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62920:24"/>
                  <head>Fifth falſe Light.</head>
                  <p>Fifthly, I might come to viſions and revelations too, for here will Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, this myſtery of iniquity, appeare likewiſe, for he muſt come with ſignes and lying wonders, God giving up men by ſtrong deluſions to believe a lye: Not that I am againſt viſions or revelations from God, but the working of Satan will be in lying viſions and wonders, filling the fancy with toyes and fleſhly exaltations: The diſcoveries and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of God are revelations full of light, power and truth, tending to the dethroning of fleſh, and the exalting of God, drawes up the ſoule into a more ſpirituall conformity to, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God; it doth not occaſion fleſhly exaltations, like unto the man of ſinne, who exalts himſelfe above all that is called God, ſaying, <hi>I am Chriſt,</hi> and ſo deceives many; but I paſſe this at preſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Sixth falſe Light.</head>
                  <p>Sixthly, I ſhall deſcend downwards againe to ſome further diſcoveries, though more fleſhly; this falſe light preſents a univerſall will and power in all men, to accept and receive grace
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62920:25"/> from God, that one man might obtain mercy as well as another, all having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like power, or at leaſt power enough to receive grace; that faith is but an act of reaſon, and they are unreaſonable men that doe not believe; not knowing that it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy; not knowing that its <hi>he that worketh to will and to doe of his good pleaſure;</hi> not experiencing that mighty power of God in thoſe who believe, ſo giving all glory to God; but rather laying the ſtreſſe of all upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, gives all to the creature; whereas ſouls rightly taught by that ſpirit of light, ſee al, not onely love and grace, but wil and power, flowing from that fountaine. And hence it is, that as ſtreames flowing from the fountain, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thither againe, ſo thoſe who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly live in grace, returne al to that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of grace; I am nothing, I can doe nothing, al flowes from that fountain: Thus the Lord alone is exalted in that ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Seventh falſe Light.</head>
                  <p>Seventhly, This falſe light preſents God to the underſtanding to be but a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62920:25"/> piece of reaſon, and ſo, that there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no God, but reaſon rules al things, and upholds al things; queſtioning, if not denying the naming of GOD; though I ſhal not queſtion, but that ſome may do it through curioſity, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome new or niſe tearme for ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities ſake through ſome temptation, yet minding the ſame thing; whereas the diſcoveries of God are plaine and familiar to his creatures: Hence the wiſedome of the Goſpel is called the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, though a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in it ſelfe, and indeed farre above the reach of reaſon, I meane the reaſon of the natural man, of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> which <hi>is of the earth, earthly:</hi> Thus from the notion of high myſtery, wee fal downe under the loweſt part of the creation of the inviſible God, by our reaſon in the creation, to judge of God to be but reaſon, who is indeed the fountaine, the Creator of reaſon, and of the whole Creation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Eighth falſe Light.</head>
                  <p>Eighthly, From hence creatures come to conclude at laſt, that the whole creation is God; that God is al things, and that al things is God; that the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62920:26"/> creation is but God brought forth into forme, and that this forme or body of Gods ſhall again become inviſible, and as at firſt; ſo at laſt there ſhal be nothing but God, no Saints, no happineſſe, no glory, no miſery, but all things return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into that one thing, God, not ſeeing God by his power bringing forth a creation, that is, not himſelfe to ſerve his pleaſure, an old creation on which he will manifeſt his juſtice; a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on which he will make knowne his grace and glory, glorifying ſome with himſelfe which are not himſelfe, though one with himſelf, and ſo as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe partakers of the ſame light, life and glory; ſo that although God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things, yet he is nothing of all thoſe things, yet the life and glory of them; he is the Creator, they but the creatures. <hi>Ninth falſe Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ninthly, And in concluſion, ſome in this falſe light come to conclude, that there is no God at all, nothing but the God of nature, or nature which is God; that all things come by nature, and are upheld by nature; and ſo at laſt turn A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, and here ends all religion; and thus <hi>the foole hath ſaid in his heart,</hi> nay, he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62920:26"/> is not now aſhamed to ſay with his tongue, <hi>that there is no God,</hi> no heaven, no hel, no good, no bad, but all is of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: now nature may take its wil, its fil of pleaſure, for what it luſts it may have, there being no God, no law unto it or above it, nothing but that law of nature which acts it ſelf in its own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in its owne liberty.</p>
                  <p>Thus (dear Chriſtian) have I, though with ſome difficulty, tract, and with much brevity diſcovered this falſe and deceivable man of ſinne, that is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, now deceiving, if it were poſſible, <hi>the very elect;</hi> not doubting but that thoſe anointings which are in you, will teach you in whom it is in truth; and keep you untill the <hi>day of his appearing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. III. Of the liberty of the law in the ſpirit.</head>
               <p>AS the law in the ſpirit is a law of light, ſo likewiſe is the law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty a law which produceth much free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſpirit where it is in truth: this the Prophet <hi>David</hi> knew by experience,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62920:27"/> when he prayed, <hi>Pſal. 50. Reſtore to me the joy of thy ſalvation, and ſtabliſh me with thy free ſpirit:</hi> Its a free ſpirit: For,</p>
               <p>1. Its freely given.</p>
               <p>2. Its a ſpirit working freedom and liberty where it is received: This ſpirit of freedom, as its a law of liberty, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers thoſe in whom it is, from al their enemies, from al their bondage and captivity.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It ſets them at liberty from ſin and Satan; I joyne them together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſinne is Satans worke, and al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men are ſervants and ſlaves to both; ſervants to Satan, enſlaved to his wil; ſervants to ſinne, willingly doing his worke; for his ſervants you are whom you obey, whether it be of ſinne unto death, or of obedience unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Now this law in the ſpirit, <hi>which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory,</hi> delivers ſouls from this captivity; from that captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſin in the conſcience, which flowes from the enlightning power of this law, which doth not only make ſoules ſenſible of ſinne, but workes likewiſe a deliverance from ſinne, and ſo ſets the ſoule at liberty from that bondage, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62920:27"/> taking away the guilt, the ſting of death, which is ſinne: This law diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering love, brings home that grace and pardon, and ſeales up the ſoule til the day of redemption, the day of its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat deliverance: And then,</p>
               <p>Secondly, It ſets the ſoule at liberty from the love and affectation of ſinne; for naturally the very affections of love and joy are captivated and enſlaved to baſe, fleſhly and carnal luſts: now this ſpirit of liberty ſets the ſoule free in its affections, through its light diſcovering the evil nature of ſinne, and ſo its power in delivering the ſoule from the love of it. Believe it, Friends, this is the light and liberty of the ſpirit, it enlightens ſoules to ſee the evil of ſinne, and where its a light enlightening, there its a law of liberty, ſetting free from the guilt, free from the love and affectation of ſinne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It workes a liberty likewiſe from ſinne in the converſation; <hi>How,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 5. 2. ſhall we who are dead to ſinne live any longer therein?</hi> Sin ſhal not reigne in the mortal body; ſin ſhal not have dominion where this law of the ſpirit is in power; neither over
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62920:28"/> the conſcience, the affections nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; this grace of God which brings home ſalvation, teacheth <hi>to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world:</hi> thus this law in the ſpirit is a law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from ſin, from Satan, whom na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men ſerve, being taken captive at his wil, and that willingly. Its true that ſoules in whom this law of liberty is manifeſt, may be taken captive, but its contrary to their mindes, it is their burden, it is their priſon, and they can ſay with <hi>Paul, O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me?</hi> And they can ſay like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe through this ſpirit of liberty, <hi>Thanks be to God through Jeſus Chriſt, though in my fleſh I ſerve the law of ſinne, yet in my minde I ſerve the law of God; And thanks be to God who giveth me a victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, This law workes a liberty from the world likewiſe, men natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being enſlaved to it, there being ſuch a ſutableneſſe unto it in the mindes of men: The firſt man being
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62920:28"/> of the earth, earthly: this firſt man lookes after nothing, delights in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe it apprehends nothing above its creation; but ſoules borne from a bone by this ſpirit of liberty, <hi>For that which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh, and that which is borne of the ſpirit is ſpirit; being created after the image of him that created them, in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe; that as they have borne the image of the earthly, now they beare the image of the heavenly;</hi> they are made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to apprehend ſpirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things; <hi>Being riſen with Chriſt, they now ſeeke after things above;</hi> things of another nature: and being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the enjoyment of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and heavenly things, that they can ſay, God is mine, Chriſt, the Spirit is mine, grace, love glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is mine (all is yours, ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> they can ſay, I am my beloveds, and my beloved is mine; now their hearts are taſten off from things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, they have a looſe affection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; they ſee now that nothing is good to them, but as they have God in it, as they have love and grace in it, being ſet at liberty from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62920:29"/> the inordinate affection to it by this ſpirit of liberty; and this is the ſecond part of the glorious liberty of the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Thoſe in whom this law of liberty is manifeſt in power, they are ſet at liberty from men, <hi>viz.</hi> from being ſlaves and ſubjects unto men in the things of God: The truth is, that men through the power and ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that ſon of perdition, have a long time, out of that pride of heart natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reſiding in them, gotten into the ſeate of God, exalting themſelves above all that is called God, have become a law in the ſpirits of men, ſubjecting and enſlaving them to their owne wils; and men through their ignorance of this law of liberty in the ſpirit, have beene, and yet for the moſt part deſire to be ſubjects and ſlaves unto them: now this ſpirit of liberty delivers ſouls from this bondage, from this ſubjection to the wils of men in the things of God; <hi>Yee are bought with a price, be yee not the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of men, 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 23. They now ſee in this light that they cannot ſerve two maſters; they now in this law of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are delivered from the fleſhly law,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62920:29"/> into the glorious liberty of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, This law ſets men at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from all other lawes beſides it ſelfe; it teacheth men not to feare thoſe who can but kil the body, and cannot kil the ſoule; it teacheth men not to act in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpiritual duty, under the power of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny command beſides it ſelfe; it ſets ſouls at liberty from being ſubject to ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; yet makes the ſoule able, in whom it is in a meaſure, to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Though all things be lawfull to me, yet I will not be brought under the power of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing;</hi> that is, of any thing beſides this law of liberty in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>This ſeems to be a doctrine of liberty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and may be an occaſion of liberty to the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Firſt, Although it ſeem to be a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of fleſhly liberty, in the eye of a carnal and fleſhly minde, yet to a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Chriſtian there is no ſuch thing; and indeed it argues, that thoſe who ſhal ſo thinke, have but little, if any knowledge at al, of the light, liberty and power of this law: The Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 1. ſaith, <hi>Stand faſt in that liberty with which Chriſt hath made you free, and be not</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62920:30"/> 
                  <hi>entangled with any yoke of bondage:</hi> Yet verſ. 13. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe not your liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi> And I ſay farther, that this law in the ſpirit teacheth men to put on a converſation ſutable to it ſelfe; it teacheth men to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts; and therefore theſe men are much miſtaken who thinke that it will teach men to be ungodly.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Its true that men of the fleſh may abuſe this heavenly law in getting a notion of it, and ſo inſtead of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, get into a carnal liberty; but mens abuſe of things through ignorance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates nothing from the excellency of that truth; this I am ſure is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſoule-ſatisfying truth, being knowne in power; this liberty from al other lawes, beſides this law of liberty, this law of life; well might the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſay, <hi>Whoſoever looks into this perfect law of liberty, and continues therein, ſhall be bleſſed in his deed, Jam.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As this law delivers ſoules out of bondage, ſo it delivers into its owne glory; as it brings ſoules out of bondage &amp; darknes, ſo it delivers them into the Kingdom of his dear Son, into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62920:30"/> But becauſe I have occaſionally mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this deliverance from bondage into a glorious liberty, in ſome other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, I have beene, and ſhall be the more briefe in this.</p>
               <p>Onely note this particular, they are delivered into the liberty of ſons: now what this liberty of ſons is, I ſhall mind in ſome few particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, A liberty to know their Father, <hi>No man knowes the Father but the Sonne, and thoſe to whom the Son reveals him;</hi> they have a liberty to know his love, his grace, his goodneſſe to them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They have a liberty to know his will likewiſe; the Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales in the ſpirits of his people his will concerning them, his will concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their juſtification, ſanctification and glory, and ſo makes their calling and election ſure to them, ſeales them up by this ſpirit unto the day of redemption; he makes knowne his will concerning his wayes and actings to the ſons of men; he doth nothing but he revealeth it to <hi>his ſervants the Prophets; To them it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdome,</hi> when it is hid from others; and thus the covenant of grace is made good in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62920:31"/> ſpirits of Chriſtians; <hi>I will write my law in their hearts, and they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt even to the greateſt;</hi> a glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to know their Fathers will, their Fathers love, their Fathers ſecrets.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The liberty of a ſon is to abide in the houſe for ever, to be one of his fathers family when the ſervant is turned out of dores.</p>
               <p>So is it with the Sons of God, made partakers of this free ſpirit, <hi>by which they can call God Father, Gal.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               <p>When ſervants who work for wages, that is, all formall profeſſors who ſerve that they may ſerve themſelves, ſhall be turned out of the family, out of the Kingdome of his dear Son, with their wages into the Kingdome of darkneſſe: When the Son ſhall remaine a Citizen of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> a member of the family and houſhold of God, under the everlaſting providence, perfection and guidance of the Almighty: When all ſervants and ſlaves ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac and Jacob, and all the Prophets, and all the ſons of God ſet down in the Kingdome of heaven at their Fathers Table, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thruſt out of dores, Luk.</hi> 13. 28. a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious word for thoſe who are eſtabliſhed with this free ſpirit.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62920:31"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The liberty of a ſon is to have communion and fellowſhip with his Father, in the knowledge of his wil, in the enjoyment of his love, in being one with his Father in all his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings: ſo is the ſpirituall Son made ſo by his free ſpirit, brought into a ſweet communion with the Father, where he partakes of love, lives in his will, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates with the Father in all his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, takes all his Fathers buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as his own, and acts with the like faithfulneſſe in it, when the ſervant he works and looks for wages, a hireling that looks not ſo much after his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters buſineſſe as after the reward, and that he accounts to be as debt unto him, the peny he lookt for, he hath it duly paid him, <hi>though many be called and few cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen;</hi> when the peny the Son looks for is ſtill to be a Son, to have more and more communion with, and conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Father, that as the Father ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the Son, ſo the Son may honour the Father, ſo as in all things to doe, and be in that condition which is ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch a calling, and all in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and power of that free ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Liberty of the ſon is to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62920:32"/> have the Fathers inheritance, to be lord of all, when the ſervant ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his wages; the ſpirituall Son ſhal be made heir, crownd with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory; although its true, a Son when a child, may be a ſervant through his minority; ſo is it with ſons, many know not their ſonſhip, <hi>Gal. 4. 1. The heir when he is a child differeth not from a ſervant, though he be lord of all; But when the fulneſſe of time is come, God ſends forth the ſpirit of his Son into their hearts, by which they call God Father;</hi> and ſo ſee themſelves now to be lords of all, heires to all their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory, crownd, not only with the titles of Sonnes, but Kings and Princes with their Father, partakers of the ſame Kingdome, of the ſame glory, in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they have it already, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is reſerved in heaven for them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, And till this glory be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated in them, they have liberty upon all occaſions to have free acceſſe into the preſence of their Father, to make known al their wants, al their wrongs; free acceſſe to the throne of grace, there obtaining mercy and finding grace; a a great helpe, a great comfort in time of need; that which the world is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62920:32"/> of, and goes without, when the prayers of unbelievers are turned into ſin, yet the prayers of his people are his delight; a great encouragement to the Saints in all their troubles, to make knowne their wants to their Father.</p>
               <p>Thus my dear ones have I given you a briefe hint of the ſons liberty and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall freedome; if the ſame ſpirit hints it to your enjoyments, then it wil be glorious; if the Son ſhall make you free, then are you free indeed, then ſtand faſt and be not entangled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yoke of bondage, for freedome is glorious, its glorious in poſſeſſion, more glorious in expectation; when you ſhall be delivered from every thing wherein is but the leaſt appearance of bondage, and be compleated in perfect freedome, which will be your glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. IV. Of falſe Liberty.</head>
               <p>I ſhall now deſcend to ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing very briefly of that falſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62920:33"/> and law in the fleſh, flowing from that ſpirit of Antichriſt now reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ruling in the hearts of the children of diſobedience; for as there is a law in the ſpirit, ſo there is a law in the fleſh rebelling againſt this law in the minde, and leading captive to the law of ſinne, this law or power of darkneſſe working in the fleſh, I ſhall diſcover briefly under theſe following conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The more common and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſort of people who account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians too; they have a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but its a falſe liberty, a liberty to doe evill, to fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, and the deſires of the fleſhly minde.</p>
               <p>Now this fleſhly liberty in the hearts of the more naturall and carnall mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, flow from one or both of theſe two principles.</p>
               <p>Firſt, From a blinde miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the good, of the pleaſure and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction the ſoule apprehends in thoſe fleſhly things; for alwaies falſe liberty flowes from falſe light, and true liberty ſucceeds true light; now the minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing naturall, and the light which is in it indeed but fleſhly, and darkneſſe it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62920:33"/> ſelfe: now in this falſe light the ſoule miſ-judging, and ſo cals evill good, and good evill; it takes a falſe liberty ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to its light: the ſoul ſeeing a good, a pleaſantneſſe, a ſweetneſſe, as it ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines in ſinne and the world, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Satan, it takes its liberty to act in it, a falſe liberty flowing from a falſe light, for the actings of al men are ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to what they ſee; unleſſ given up to a ſpirit of <hi>ſlumber</hi> ſo, as to quench the true diſcoveries that ſometimes God makes forth to them, and they cannot but owne it; therefore all you carnall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines had need to looke about your ſelves, for at preſent you ſeem to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to a great judgement, blindneſſe of minde, not to ſee good when it cometh, but to cal evill good, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe light, to hardneſſe of heart, to ſin, and follow the luſts of the fleſh with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of minde, thinking God to be like your-ſelvs; but he will reprove you, and ſet your ſins in order before you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or from a miſ-apprehenſion and application of Gods gracious love in giving Chriſt; hence the natural crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hearing of free mercy, grace and love to ſinners, drawes this concluſion,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62920:34"/> That now it may take liberty to ſinne the more freely: Why? Becauſe God is mercifull, and Chriſt died for ſinners. And thus creatures abuſe mercy, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling under foot, as much as in them lyeth, the grace of God; a high deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and a body requitall of grace and love, to offend grace becauſe it is grace; to ſinne becauſe God is mercifull: Oh horrid wickedneſſe! <hi>What, ſhall we ſinne becauſe grace abounds? God forbid!</hi> But this falſe liberty in and after the fleſh, will produce a bad requitall if grace prevent not: See <hi>Rom. 2. 4, 5. Or deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe, and forbearance, and long-ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance; but after thine hardneſſe and impenitent heart treaſureſt up to thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous judgement of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Come to the more zealous, and their liberty is in the fleſh likewiſe, a liberty to be ſervants of men; a liberty to ſerve God, as they thinke, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too in a fleſhly way of obedience: And to but hear of this liberty in ſpirit is bondage unto them; and thus it ſeems to be their liberty to be ſlaves to others,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62920:34"/> Lords to other lawes: then this law of true liberty in the ſpirit to fulfil a fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteouſneſſe, ſeemes to be their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to be ſubject to the wils of men, and ſo to become the ſervants of men, ſeemes to be their liberty; a liberty which truly is, and will end in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; and this falſe liberty flows like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from falſe light.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Come to others who have paſs't through this life of zeale to the wils of men, and to their owne wils, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten a notion, not only of grace and love, but of this ſpirit of liberty, (and onely a notion) they preſently apprehending, as they thinke, that all is now good, they ſeeing no actions to be differing to them, but all ſeemes to be alike; they freely take a liberty from this falſe light to act after the fleſh; it is their liberty to be prophane, carnall, looſe, unprofitable, and ſo indeed they make uſe of their liberty which is a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall one, as an occaſion to the fleſh; they ſinne as they ſay not only becauſe grace abounds, but becauſe the ſpirit teacheth them ſo to doe, which is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of liberty; and indeed its to be doubted that they are poſſeſt with ſuch a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62920:35"/> ſpirit of liberty after the fleſh, that all bonds of righteouſneſſe and true liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are broken; and in this I may ſpeak in the Apoſtles words, <hi>Phil. 3. 18. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny walke, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you weeping, that are enemies to the croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame, who minde earthly things.</hi> And thus poore creaturs being given up to work al wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe with greedineſſe, doe not only act thoſe things themſelves, but have pleaſure in them that doe them; ſo that to walke humbly with God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in their eyes, not onely a bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, but a ſcorne; and thoſe who talk of it, barbarous; a thing ſo low as not to be underſtood.</p>
               <p>Thus whereas Saints have a liberty from ſinne, theſe have a liberty in ſinne; Saints have a liberty to be the Sons of God, theſe have a liberty to be the ſons of Satan, of darkneſſe, and yet pretend themſelves to be the Sons of God; but his ſervants you are to whom you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, <hi>whether it be of ſin unto death, or of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62920:35"/>
               <head>Chap. V. Of the righteouſneſſe of the Law in the ſpirit.</head>
               <p>AS this law in the ſpirit is a law of light and liberty, ſo it is a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous law, that is, a law working righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in thoſe in whom it is, making ſoules partakers of its own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is indeed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God; <hi>He was made ſin for us, that we might be made the righeeouſneſse of God in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 21.</p>
               <p>Now the righteouſneſſe of this law may be produced unto theſe two heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An internal righteouſneſſe, as it hath relation to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An external righteouſneſſe, as it hath relation to men.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As it hath relation to God, and ſo it is a righteouſneſſe in the ſpirit; this may be conſidered likewiſe under theſe two heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it is more external.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it is more internal.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As it is more external, yes, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62920:36"/> and the righteouſneſſe of God too, becauſe prepared by the Father for ſinners, brought home and applyed by the ſpirit: and this is the righteouſneſſe of God in relation to what he hath done for them; in laying helpe upon one that is mighty; in laying iniquity upon Chriſt, and condemning it there: that ſo through the apprehending and applying of the Fathers love in this great worke, the guilt of ſin might be taken out of the conſcience, through the ſoules apprehending, the Father do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in Chriſt for it, which it ſelfe could not doe; <hi>For what the law could not doe in that it was weake through the fleſh, God ſending his owne Son in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſin condemned ſin in the fleſh,</hi> Rom, 8. 3. Herein the ſoule beholding and enjoying love from the Father, ſees it ſelfe now to be juſtified, and that by grace, from al things by which it could not be juſtified by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> this is a more external righteouſneſſe becauſe wrought for us, without us; yet the righteouſneſſe of God, of the ſpirit, becauſe prepared by God, eyed and applyed in the light and power of the ſpirit.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62920:36"/>
               <p>2. That which I cal a more ſpiritual righteouſneſſe, it is a righteouſneſſe wrought within us by this law of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; and this righteouſneſſe wrought for us, without us, though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in us, is but a precedent to this righteouſneſſe wrought within; that ſo the righteouſneſſe of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit: this is that myſtery of Chriſt in you, the hope of glory, the forming of Chriſt within, that is, when the ſoule hath experience of the ſame ſpirit within as was and is in Chriſt, working the ſoule into a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual conformity to Chriſt, growing up in him, til it come to the ſame fulneſſe, to the ſame perfection; but both theſe I have in a meaſure unfolded in another Treatiſe, and therefore paſſe it with the more brevity in this place; onely I ſhal anſwer one Objection by the way, and ſo paſſe to the ſecond part of the righteouſneſſe of this law in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Some wil be ready to ſay, <hi>That they know no ſuch thing as this law in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit juſtifying, this externall forming of Christ, they know Chriſt no other waies but as he dyed</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62920:37"/> 
                  <hi>at Jeruſalem, and that this talk of Chriſt within ſeems to be a mystery, if not a deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for Chriſt dwels in his people, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but by faith, that is ſouls beleeving only what he hath done for them, and that there is no other forming of Chriſt in them, till the day of reſurrection of their bodies from the grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer firſt, That its true this forming of Chriſt within is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery indeed, the compleater of it will be the top and height of all myſtery, this is the myſtery, Chriſt in you, the hope of glory, that is, the ſaid ſpirit and power conforming ſouls to Chriſt in death, reſurrection and life, and this is the more myſterious man of ſinne, the antichriſt, who denies Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, this myſtery of Chriſt in you the hope of glory. And although ſome may abuſe this truth, this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being deluded only with the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, yet let others take heed they abuſe it not through ignorance.</p>
               <p>2. I anſwer, that whereas the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, Chriſt dwels in the heart by faith: It's true, but there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold dwelling of Chriſt in the heart by faith: the firſt is, when the ſoul ſees and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62920:37"/> believes what God in Chriſt hath done for it: and ſecondly, when the ſoul ſees and beleeves that this Chriſt, that is the ſame ſpirit that dwelt in Chriſt dwels in him, as a law of light, life and liberty in him, ſeeing the law of the ſpirit of life that was in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, freeing it from the law of ſinne and death: for the ſoul taught of God ſees and beleeves both theſe to be a truth, Chriſt for, and Chriſt in the ſoul: this we ſhall finde clearly held forth in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, not ſetting up the one in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other, but you ſhall finde that the Scripture preſents you with a death with Chriſt, and reſurrection with him <hi>Rom. 5. Phil.</hi> 3. 10. with a life with him, <hi>John 14. 19. Becauſe I live ye ſhall live alſo,</hi> and in him by vertue of ſpirituall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>verſ. 20. At that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you:</hi> Note a word by the way, at that day they ſhall know it, At what day? in that day when Chriſt reveals himſelf in them, <hi>The world ſhall ſee me no more, but ye ſhall ſee me:</hi> It is not ſuch a ſight as the Apoſtles had of Chriſt, when he was with them in the fleſh: it is not ſuch a ſight as the world had, or at this day
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62920:38"/> have of Chriſt: for the world beleeves that Chriſt died for ſinners, yet they ſee him not, now Saints ſee him firſt dying for them. 2. They ſee him li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them: and this aſſurance of Chriſt in them; they receive by faith, beleeving and knowing this to be a truth, for faith and knowledge in this particular is but one thing, <hi>We beleeve, and know,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, that thou art the Chriſt the Sonne of the living God.</hi> And thus Saints in whom this law of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is manifeſt, can in a meaſure ſay, We beleeve and know that God hath revealed his Sonne not only to us, but in us: and thus Chriſt dwels in the heart by faith, and there is no one truth of God more clearly revealed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, more glorious in the ſpirits of Saints then this truth of Chriſt formed in them.</p>
               <p>2. I come now to the ſecond part of the righteouſneſſe of this law in the ſpirit, which is an external righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amongſt men, for this law in the ſpirit, teacheth men to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in the world: God is a righteous God, and this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous law conforms ſouls unto this
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62920:38"/> righteous God; and where there is an internall, there will be likewiſe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall righteouſneſſe. And this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in converſation may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under theſe two heads:</p>
               <p>1. In the abſtaining from workes of unrighteouſnes amongſt men, and they are ſuch as theſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8. oppreſſion and fraudulency, or ſuch as are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>verſ. 9. Know you not that the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall not inherit the Kingdome of God: Be not deceived, neither fornicatours nor ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, nor adulterers, &amp;c. ſhall inherit the Kingdome of God:</hi> Theſe are works of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe; that is, works that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare men to be unrighteous.</p>
               <p>2. In performing viſible workes of righteouſneſſe, <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works:</hi> faith ever produceth workes, works of piety, and works of charity: in a word, this law of righteouſneſſe in the ſpirit, makes good that word of righteouſneſſe in them; <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould doe unto you, ſo doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, for this is the law and the Prophets.</hi> It puts the man in whom it is, in all his dealings amongſt men in the other balance; and this is the rule of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with others, to do as he would be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62920:39"/> done unto, the true rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amongſt men; and truly this law of righteouſneſſe is that I long to ſee more abundantly manifeſt in the Saints, in theſe later daies, for God hath a glorious dſpenſation of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to bring forth in his Saints, and through them to the world, that the righteous God appearing with ſo much ſplendour, glory and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his people, and through them to the world, that the world ſhall be driven to fall down, and acknowledge God is in them of a truth: he will take out of them that perverſe and peeviſh ſpirit, and fill them with the ſpirit of love: he will take out of them that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſpirit of unrighteouſneſſe, and fill them with the ſpirit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, juſtice and equity, and this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearance of righteouſneſſe in them, will by them and through them bring to nought the unrighteouſneſſe and oppreſſion that is in the world: for as the wrath of God was, ſo now it is much more abundantly made manifeſt againſt all unrighteouſneſſe of men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all unrighteouſneſſe within, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all unrighteouſneſſe without his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62920:39"/> people: and this ſhall be effected by the glorious appearance of this glorious law of righteouſneſſe in them. See <hi>Iſa. 45. 14. And they</hi> (to wit, men of the world) <hi>ſhall be thine, they ſhall come after thee in chains, they ſhall come over, and they ſhall fall down unto thee, making ſupplication, ſaying, Surely God is in thee, and there is none elſe,</hi> there is no God: Thus ſhall a King reign in righteouſneſſe, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall rule in judgement, although its true never more oppreſſion then now under the pretence of liberty, a great argument that the time is at hand, and then ſhall all oppreſſours and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fall to the ground, and the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhall be exalted in that day, then ſhall ye return and ſee the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him that ſerved God, and him that ſerved him not: for unto them that fear his name ſhall this ſonne of righteouſneſſe ariſe (filling them with righteouſneſſe) with healing under his wings, and they ſhall goe forth and grow up as calves in the ſtall: but this day of the Lord ſhall burn like an oven, and all the proud, and all oppreſſours, and all that doe wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble: the day cometh that ſhall burn
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62920:40"/> them up, and leave them neither root nor branch, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 1, 2. This is the day of the Lord, the day of fire that is coming upon the face of the earth: Let the voice of <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet be a warning unto men, leſt he come and ſmite the earth with a curſe. How then ſhould the ſpirits of Chriſtians be up to the Lord in a way of waiting for the more full revelation of this righteous law within them, that they may ſee all enemies both within them and without them made a footſtoole unto this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous diſpenſation, that the world may not have cauſe to ſay, as formerly, that they profeſſe more then others, but they are as covetous as any, as proud, peeviſh and hard hearted as any, as full of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion as any, by which meanes the name of God hath been blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the world; But when they ſhal reade in the carriage of Chriſtians no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but love, and righteouſneſſe, and in-offenſive walking, a diſpoſition al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to doe good, and that unto all; I ſay when this appearance of God is manifeſt in the Saints, it ſhall throw downe that wickedneſſe, that pride and that oppreſſion which is in the world:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62920:40"/> Waite therefore upon God for it, <hi>For bleſſed are they that waite for him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VI. The unrighteous Law.</head>
               <p>I Shal come now briefly in a word or two likewiſe to ſpeake a word in the diſcovery of that falſe law of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or rather unrighteouſneſſe that dwels in the hearts of natural men; and I ſhal minde it under theſe two heads likewiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it is within them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it is manifeſt without them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As it is within them, and that under ſeverall notions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some thinking their civility and morality to be a perfect law and rule of righteouſneſſe in them, having good natures, doing as they thinke, and ſay no body wrong, they thinke this ſhal be their righteouſneſſe, which is but a rghteouſneſſe of fleſh, and not of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others looke at, and talke of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62920:41"/> Chriſt dying for ſin, not being made partaker of any power, by which they are dead to ſin, and yet expect a juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a righteouſneſſe, a ſalvation in the end from the death of ſin, this is a falſe law of unrighteouſneſſe in the mindes of moſt, not believing <hi>that the wages of ſin is death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Others come higher then this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of joining Chriſt and duty together, fleſh and ſpirit as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workers together, talking of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt, but looking for it as it were, by the works of the law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed ignorant of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, theſe are zealous, but not according to knowledge; and this is looked after, and pleaded for, as a high degree of righteouſneſſe, when perhaps there is no more in it then what <hi>Paul</hi> accounted loſſe, yea, dung and droſſe, for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus his Lord; and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer the loſſe of al ſuch things, as grounds of righteouſneſſe, that he might win Chriſt, and be found in him. Good it were, and much mercy to ſuch, if they could with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſuffer the loſſe of al ſuch righteouſneſſe, in a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62920:41"/> way of grace, for it muſt be loſt firſt or laſt; if not til laſt, then they muſt be bid depart from al their workes, as workes and workers of iniquity, <hi>into utter darkneſſe, where ſhall be a lake of fire, which will occaſion weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Others ſeem to come higher then this again, ſeeming to be delivered from workes, as it is their righteouſneſſe, and are al for Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe, free juſtification without workes, but they are ignorant of, if not enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the righteouſneſſe of this law in the ſpirit: Although I queſtion not, but that many who are yet come no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be precious, and enjoy true comfort according to that meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, yet theſe two things are conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That many are likely to periſh, after come forth of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, before they come into this land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> this land of reſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That thoſe who truly know Chriſt without them to be their righteouſneſſe, doe, or ſhal likewiſe know Chriſt within them, although at preſent through ignorance they deny
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62920:42"/> it, although its that which is or ſhal be their greateſt glory; but I ſay for a man onely to know Chriſt without him, glorying in this, without any experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the life of Chriſt in him, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made conformable unto him, this is a fleſhly and deceivable law of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Others ſeeme, as they ſay, to come higher then al the reſt into a way of righteouſneſſe, although loweſt of al; for they looke not after morality nor legality, nor Chriſt, nor this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous law in the ſpirit, which is the ſubſtance and perfection of al; but they have found a new law of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or rather of unrighteouſneſſe, that is, the law of the fleſh, doe what they wil its al good, juſtifiable, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but to ſuch I ſay, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked; For what you ſowe you are like to reape; For God is not as man, that he ſhould lie, or as the ſon of man, that he ſhould repent; Let God be righteous, let God be true, and all falſe and fleſhly perſwaſions be a lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. The external <hi>unrighteouſneſſe</hi> of this deceivable law in the fleſh may be conſidered either,</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62920:42"/>
               <p>1. Doing or acting things contrary to the true rule of <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> thus either,</p>
               <p>Firſt, In acting, that ſo they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unto men to be righteous, like unto hypocrites; and this ſatisfies, if there can be ſuch a viſible walking as may ſilence men, though <hi>hypocriſy, deceit</hi> and <hi>unrighteouſneſſe</hi> lie hid and lurking within; theſe are the whited Tombes Chriſt ſpeakes of which appear beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful before men, <hi>when within they are full of dead mens bones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Or elſe when men take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to appear outward to men as they liſt, ful of al <hi>unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and yet thinke to be innocent, righteous and cleare before God, juſtifying themſelves that they have good hearts, and the like: theſe are they the Lord reproves by the Prophet, <hi>Will you ſteal, murder, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery, and ſweare falſly? and yet come and ſtand before God in his houſe, thinking to be delivered, ſaying, They ſhall have peace, though they walke after the ſtubborneſſe of their own hearts, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Others not onely making <hi>gaine to be their godlineſſe,</hi> but gaine to be their rule of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> to others and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62920:43"/> hence it comes to paſs oft-times that they have a law of liberty within them to lie and coſen for advantage, not knowing that righteous rule, <hi>To doe as they would be done unto:</hi> and this gain ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage is the great rule by which moſt in the world walk: I wiſh I had not cauſe to ſay, that its the rule of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who would be accounted more then ordinary Chriſtians, which occaſions (in the fourth place) much oppreſſion and fraudulency; now there is a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to defraud, oppreſs, to doe any thing for advantage; this is the unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this law in the fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VII. The law of true holineſſe.</head>
               <p>THis law in the ſpirit is likewiſe a law of holines and purity in whom it is: this law of the Lord is pure, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying and purging ſoules: God is a holy God, and he works the ſpirits of his people into his own likenes; hence
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62920:43"/> it is the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18. ſaith, <hi>That all we with open face beholding as in a glaſſe the glory of God, are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, even as by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord.</hi> The Spirit and glory of the Lord is a transforming Spirit and glory, it never leaves thoſe in whom its manifeſt, until it change them into the very image and glory of the Father: This law of holineſſe as it works holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſpirits of Saints may be conſidered under two heads likewiſe, either more internall, or more exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
               <p n="1">1. More internally, as it changes and reneweth the minde: for this ſpirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to worke holineſſe firſt within, it reneweth the ſpirit of the minde, it takes poſſeſſion of the heart: it doth not only ſay, <hi>My ſonne give me thy heart,</hi> but it takes the heart and moulds it, and forms it according to its own good pleaſure: it doth not onely ſay, <hi>Be ye holy,</hi> but it works holineſs, and ſaith, likewiſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt be holy:</hi> hence it is called, <hi>The holy, the ſanctifying Spirit;</hi> not only in reſpect of its own purity, but as it workes purity in the ſpirits of Saints: Thus holineſſe becomes the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62920:44"/> houſe of the Lord for ever: every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, every Saint is Gods houſe, his temple, his habitation, in them hee dwels, and that by way of union and ſpiritual communion; and therefore holines becomes this houſe, this habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What is holineſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Holines in ſpirit it is, when the inner man by the power and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit is changed and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by which means the old man fleſh, is put off with his deeds, and the new man is put on: it is an inward change from fleſh to ſpirit, being made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the divine nature, of the nature of the holy God: hence it comes to paſs that the minde being thus renewed ſo earneſtly preſſes after more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this ſanctity: now the ſoul ſees clearly what was the Fathers everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purpoſe concerning him, to gather him up into the ſame perfection of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſs with himſelfe: this indeed being the Saints perfection, the Saints glory, the putting off of al fleſh, the filth of the old man, and to be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in this holineſs of the new: And he that hath this hope in him purifieth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62920:44"/> himſelf, even as Chriſt is pure, that ſoul hath no patern or perfection ſhort of him who is their elder brother, who is entered into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> the holy of holies, the moſt holy place, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection it ſelf, and a way being opened for Saints to follow him. Hence it is they with ſo much earneſtneſs preſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not as if they had already attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or were already perfect; but they preſs forward, if by any meanes they might attain the reſurrection from the dead, that is a full deliverance from this body of death into the compleat and perfect glory and purity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Thus this law in the ſpirit is a law of holineſs, of ſanctification, it doth not leave men carnal, and fleſhly, and filthy; no no the will of God is your ſanctification; and this he works, where he manifeſts himſelf; he truly effects in the mindes of his people (which is his houſe) what he did in the temple at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> he over-turned the tables of the money-changers, and whipt the buiers and ſellers out of the temple: ſo hee doth in the ſpirits of his people, whips out all thoſe unclean luſts and fleſhly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62920:45"/> imaginations which defile this holy temple, not but that there may be the preſence of theſe, but they are not there with delight, with content: and this ſanctifying ſpirit wil never leave them til hee hath turned them al out, the <hi>God of peace will tread Satan under feet ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and all thoſe enemies ſhall become the Saints foot-ſtool; this is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eies: this is the Lords work, and he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it in his time: Let all thoſe who wait upon him for the accompliſhment of it cry grace, grace unto it, the end of it wil be glory in the higheſt, when al fleſh ſhall vail it ſelfe to this excellent glory, though it be not accompliſhed as ſoon as you expect it, yet aſſuredly the end wil be glorious, that is, it will crown al your temptations, and trials, expectations, when you ſhal partake of this perfect change.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is an external holines like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that is a viſible demonſtration in the converſation of what is wrought within: There is not onely holineſſe within, but without; The Kings daughter is not only all glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but her cloathing likewiſe is of nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-work:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62920:45"/> There is a viſible manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a renewed minde, where the God of peace ſanctifies he doth it through out not only in ſoul and ſpirit, but in body too. Hence it is the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Be ye holy in all manner of holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and godlineſſe.</hi> This outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of holineſſe is but the fruit of that tree of holines within, and where this tree is, this fruit wil appear, there wil be fruit unto holines, and the end e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life.</p>
               <p>This external holines appeares under theſe two particulars:</p>
               <p>Firſt, In the forſaking evil cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In the performing or acting that which is good.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the forſaking evil there is not only an evil root, but there is evil fruit, the fruit of the fleſh: now where this law of holineſs and purity is, there is a purging of al filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit. This is that the Apoſtle minds, 1 <hi>Cor. 6. Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are purged by the Spirit of our God,</hi> &amp;c. This is the true property of this law in the ſpirit, to make clear not only within, but without too: <hi>Waſh</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:62920:46"/> 
                  <hi>you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes,</hi> Iſa. 1. <hi>ceaſe to doe evil;</hi> &amp;c. al filthines and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe flows directly from the law of the fleſh, and are the fruits of the fleſh; the tree is knowne by his fruit. It is altogether unpoſſible for a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, changed, ſanctified heart to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to the luſts of the fleſh: they are fruits that grow in the devils garden, upon the tree of nature, and not of grace; they are the fruit that grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the forbidden tree, whoſoever eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thereof is dead; if you walk after the fleſh ye are dead, but if by the ſpirit ye mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, ye are alive: Therefore take this in a word for al, That it is altogether unpoſſible for a man that lives in the ſpirit to bring forth fruits after the fleſh; they who live after the fleſh ſavour the things of the fleſh: Only two cautions conſidered,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That thoſe who live after the ſpirit, may be, and oft are burdened with fleſh.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Although they are burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with fleſh, yet they walke not, they warre not after the fleſh, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62920:46"/> in them ſubdues and deſtroyes fleſh, and the converſation is in a meaſure ſutable to ſuch a ſpiritual law within.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This holines appears not onely in the forſaking that which is viſibly evil, and carries a clear appearance in it to be of the fleſh: But likewiſe</p>
               <p>2. In the viſible acting and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing works of holines ſutable to ſuch an inward principle: the ſoule does not only now ceaſe to do evil, but learns to doe wel; This is that the Scripture ſo often mindes, and Saints ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienceth, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good workes may glorifie your Father that is in heaven:</hi> And this is the wil of God even your ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that you may know how to poſſeſſe your veſſels in ſanctification and honour, and the tree is known by his fruit, <hi>Does a man gather grapes of thorns or figs of thistls: And the good man out of the good treaſure of his heart bringeth forth good things; but the evil man out of the evil treaſure of his heart bringeth forth evil things.</hi> Thus Scripture clears this truth; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience likewiſe manifeſts it, Thoſe who are taught of the Spirit can beare
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62920:47"/> witneſs unto this truth, That the more that ſpirit of holineſs appeares within, purifying the inner man, the more viſible does that holines appear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But it may be queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>What are theſe workes of holineſſe that viſibly appeare thus in the ſanctified man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Negative: I minde not cuſtoms and forms, for in this natural men may act far: But</p>
               <p>2. Affirmatively: 1. In ſpeaking forth and declaring the goodneſs, holineſs and love of God: A heart that is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied indeed, and enjoyes love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion indeed, cannot but according to the meaſure enjoyed, and the gift received, but declare it forth unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> Thus Saints cannot keepe ſilence when God ſpeakes in them, but are ever and anon breathing forth the good, the love of God; then ſaith the ſoul, <hi>Truly God is good, O taſte and ſee that the Lord is gracious. Oh that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare his wonderfull love to the ſonnes of men:</hi> The ſoul can now ſay, <hi>God is good,</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:62920:47"/> 
                  <hi>he is ſweet, he is lovely, and altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull.</hi> Thus Saints are not either firſt breathing forth fleſhly and carnal diſcourſe, unprofitable and vain things, but their words are <hi>alwaies ſeaſoned with ſalt, that it may miniſter grace unto the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> neither are they dumb and tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied alwaies, not but that thoſe who are precious may be ſlow of ſpeech; but being drawne forth, ſomething they have to declare of God: They are not firſt altogether empty, and ſo ſilent, that argues a barren, fruitleſs, unſanctified ſoul; neither ſecondly doe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be high in knowledge, but wil not declare any thing, except fleſh talk of ſpirit, and manifeſt fleſh, no, they cannot with-hold the truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, nor hide his goodneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, as by ſtealth; but ſtill, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh,</hi> and the <hi>tree is known by his fruit.</hi> God creating in his people the fruit of the lips, <hi>peace, peace to them who are afarre off, and to them who are nigh:</hi> And as this fruit of the lips appeares in ſpeaking of GOD, ſo likewiſe in ſpeaking to GOD both in prayer and praiſe.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62920:48"/>
               <p>2. There is the fruit likewiſe of the converſation as wel as of the lips; there is not onely the fruit of ſaying but do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>If any man doe my will he ſhall know,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this doing conſiſts either,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In doing workes of piety accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power and liberty recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In doing workes of righteous ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equity, not in ſeeking alone our owne, but others good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In doing workes of mercy both to the ſoules and bodies of thoſe who want, elſe you may ſee the fruits of this ſpirit, <hi>Gal. 5. 22. The fruit of the ſpirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſse, faith, meekneſſe, temperance, againſt ſuch there is no law;</hi> Theſe are the fruits of the ſpirit, which being manifeſt, makes God, and truth, and Saints ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare lovely, not onely each to other, but to the world likewiſe; they ſhall fall downe and confeſſe, <hi>That God is in you of a truth:</hi> Theſe fruits of the ſpirit <hi>Peter</hi> mindes, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 5. Adde to faith virtue, &amp; to your virtue knowledg, &amp; to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge patience, and to patience temperance, and to temperance godlineſſe, and to godlineſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:62920:48"/> 
                  <hi>brotherly kindneſſe, and to brotherly kindneſſe charity:</hi> Thus the true Chriſtian hath a holy converſation, holy within and holy without, holineſſe written upon the horſes bridles, every pot in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> appeares to be holy, in al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of holy converſation and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; a univerſall walking with, and conformity to God in ſpirit, ſoule and body; <hi>Their converſation is in heaven,</hi> their hearts there, their minde, their comfort and communion, and it appeares by their walking before men, in their word and actions, that it is ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. VIII. Of falſe or fleſhly holineſſe.</head>
               <p>AS there is a <hi>holineſſe</hi> in the ſpirit, ſo likewiſe there is a holineſſe after the fleſh, ſo accounted, ſo called, though it be indeed but unholineſſe, for the man of ſinne imitates Chriſt in every particular; and I believe that there hath been as great a miſtake in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of holineſſe, in taking it to be what
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62920:49"/> it is not, as in any one particular: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhal minde a word or two brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the diſcovery of this myſtery of iniquity.</p>
               <p>1. This myſtery of iniquity, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of holineſſe when it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but fleſh, may be conſidered ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
               <p>Firſt, As it workes within, and that either,</p>
               <p>1. Looking upon good purpoſes and good reſolutions to amend and to doe better.</p>
               <p>Or elſe, 2. In a good minde to leave ſin, but it wants power; a good, a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heart, though a bad converſation, not knowing that good purpoſes are common to the worſt of men, and that where there is a bad outſide, there is a worſe inſide; for if the ſtreames be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, the fountaine is much more filthy; <hi>For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh;</hi> and the outward man acts: an ungodly converſation alwaies flowes from an unſanctified ſoule; if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be light, vain and fooliſh, the heart is much more light and vain; for all prodigality, prophaneneſſe and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath its firſt riſe in the heart; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62920:49"/> it is the Lord ſaith, <hi>My ſon, give me thy heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or 3. Not only in having a minde to leave it, but likewiſe in having ſome hatred againſt it, and from hence a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking of it, becauſe it ſees an evill, a danger in it; perhaps it now appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends, that the wages of ſin is death, and it feares hell, and the eternall flames ſpoken of in Scripture; and from hence growes out of liking with it, when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps elſe it could be content many times to embrace it; thus moſt men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name and notion of Chriſtian, deceive themſelves with a fleſhly fancy of holineſſe in the heart, when indeed, and in truth it is nothing more then fleſhly deluſions, and that which is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually found in the hearts of naturall men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, There is likewiſe a moſt outward appearance of holineſſe in the fleſh, which is indeed but fleſhly; and this may be diſcovered, either,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the more common and carnall ſort, who account that now and then the performance of a good act is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make them holy, and that their good acts will weigh downe their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62920:50"/> evill, they thinke that <hi>Lord have mercy upon me,</hi> or now and then a good prayer is enough to make them holy, though perhaps they take the more liberty to ſinne by meanes thereof; a wonderfull deluſion in the mindes of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others come higher perhaps in an outward civility, and an externall acting in the uſe of Ordinances; they will goe to Church, as they call it, and heare Sermons too, perhaps have their Infants ſprinkled, go to the Sacrament, as they call it, &amp;c. And this is a high degree of holineſſe in the mindes of moſt; how doe poore creatures bleſſe themſelves in ſuch vaine and empty formes and faſhions to their owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing? For this is that which is ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to nature to act in theſe low and formall waies after the doctrines and precepts of men, or after the fleſhly imaginations of the vaine and deceitful heart, and not after Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Others come higher then this, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an univerſall, as they ſuppoſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and forſaking of ſin, to the acting and performing of that which is good; and thus it is much in doing and acting, looking upon outward actings to be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62920:50"/> their holineſſe; and here hath lien a myſterious myſtery of iniquity both in Miniſters and People, the one teaching, the other practiſing ſuch a holineſſe; Hence is it that Miniſters when they would preach people in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, they preſſe them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſinne, to weepe and mourne, pray, and heare Sermons, to be much in duty, and this without all peradventure was enough to make them holy, never looking after that internall ſpirit of holineſſe which occaſions thoſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal actings, ſutable to ſuch an internall principle: Hence it comes to paſſe that many poore ſoules being thus miſ-led, come under a ſpirit of deluſion, or elſe under a ſpirit of bondage, being ſenſible of its coming ſhort in performance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily told, that if thou canſt not mourne, and pray, and performe ſuch and ſuch duties, then thou art no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but Satan rules in thee. Now the difference betweene the performance of the externall actings lieth principally in theſe two things; the one acts in it as under a taske, a burden, a bondage, and he hath no comfort till the thing is done; the other acts in liberty and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62920:51"/> freedome of ſpirit, God is his portion without any ſuch acting, and God is his portion in it, he hath communion with God without it, and that is it he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects in it.</p>
               <p>3. The one acts in duty that he might be holy, lookes upon himſelfe that the more he is in exerciſing and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the more holy he is; the other acts in externals, becauſe he is holy that is made partaker of that ſpirit of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all true actions flowing from that fountain of light, life, liberty and love; and thus moſt under ſeverall forms and apprehenſions live low and fleſhly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelves with a fleſhly holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a holineſſe conſiſting in formes formes and creature actings, taking the ſhadow for the ſubſtance, the fruit for the tree, nay or, rather the falſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable fruit of the fleſh, for both the tree and fruit of holineſſe in the ſpirit, but thoſe who <hi>ſow to the fleſh ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. I ſhall adde in the fourth place, though I might have mentioned it in the firſt, that fleſhly law of unholineſſe that dwels in the hearts of all naturall men, and yet they bleſſe themſelves in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:62920:51"/> their preſent condition: There is, and ever hath beene a naturall antipathy in the hearts of all men, naturally againſt God, and the appearance of holineſſe in truth in his people; ſuch is the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of the hearts of naturall men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holineſſe of God, that they ever did, and doe to this day oppoſe it; this is the law of unholineſſe that dwels, that rules in the hearts of all naturall men; and hence it comes to paſſe that men naturally are taken up with fancies and ſhadowes inſtead of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſomething they muſt have to quiet them, but not the truth, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that affrights them, becauſe they are ignorant of it, and have an enmity againſt it; hence it is they call evill good and good evill, they put light for darkneſſe and darkneſſe for light, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62920:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:62920:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:62920:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62920:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:62920:54"/>
               <head>Chap. IX. Of the power of the law in the ſpirit.</head>
               <p>I Shall now proceed to ſpeake a word of the power of this Covenant of grace, this law in the ſpirit; for as it is a law of light, liberty, righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, it creates a new man within in righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo its a law of power and much glory, <hi>We preach Chriſt,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>the power of God and the wiſedome of God:</hi> This is that word which is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in operation, and powerfull, ſharper then any two edged ſword, it enters in to the dividing of the joints and the marrow; it is a ſearcher of the thoughts and intents of the heart, the power of this law in the ſpirit: This Covenant of grace made within the Saints may be diſcovered under ſeverall conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The power of this law is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing power, it over-powers the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men, it convinces men of ſin, of righteouſneſſe, and of judgement; it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62920:54"/> convinceth them of ſinne, making them truely and deepely ſenſible of it. Of righteouſneſſe, making ſoules ſenſible of the unrighteouſneſſe of all their beſt righteouſneſſe. Of judgement, that al thoſe things delighted in formerly muſt be judged, muſt receive the ſentence of death from Jeſus Chriſt, ſitting as a refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and purifier in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It converts as wel as convinceth, it changeth and reneweth the minde, takes off the minde from ſinne, it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the minde, and the converſation, it makes a ſeparation between the ſoule and ſinne, it ſeparates betweene a man, and his beloved luſts; it converts a ſoul from the love of ſinne, it converts it likewiſe from the practice of ſinne, it worketh a real change within, which produceth a change without. This is that power which overcomes fleſh, world and devil; what's the reaſon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a poor ſoul would many times glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be rid of ſinne, but they want a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, not being ſenſible where their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lieth, but perhaps oppoſe fleſh in the ſtrength of fleſh, when its proper onely to the ſpirit to deſtroy fleſh? Therefore let Saints be informed where their
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62920:55"/> power lieth that they may wait upon God whoſe worke it is to ſubdue all things in them, all things without them, that are contrary to him in his time.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As it convinceth and converteth, ſo it makes thoſe in whom it is a free and a willing people, <hi>In the day of thy power thy people ſhall be a willing people,</hi> Pſa. 110. Willing to have ſinne ſacrificed, luſt and corruption ſubdued; willing in the beauty of holineſs to offer up ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſacrifice acceptable to God in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; its this powerful ſpirit which works in us <hi>both to wil &amp; to do of his good pleaſure:</hi> nothing in the world is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to over-power the wil, and make it free, but this free ſpirit of power, its this ſpirit which makes ſoules willing to yeeld up themſelves to the ſcepter of the Almighty, which makes ſoules free and willing ſubjects to the King of Kings, that fils them with joy at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of his preſence, of his power, that ſaith not with the world, <hi>He is come to torment them before the time,</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiceth becauſe the Lord God omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent reigns, topping and keeping under all other lawes and powers beſides it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62920:55"/> ſelfe. Thus the Lord reignes, and the Saints rejoyce, the Lord reigns, and the world trembles.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The power of this inviſible, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual law wil appear in the deſtruction of Antichriſt that man of ſinne, that ſon of perdition, this hee will effect by the ſpirit of his mouth, and the brightneſs of his coming. The coming of Chriſt in the ſpirit, which is the glorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of this law, is that power that muſt deſtroy Antichriſt. By An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt that man of ſinne I underſtand any thing within us, or without us, whether it appeare in wiſdome or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; if it be of the fleſh though its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences be never ſo fair and glorious, yet it is but an Antichriſt, a man of ſin, a ſon of perdition: its true all the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of fleſh is againſt Chriſt, but there are workings in a more higher and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious way, and then its the more decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, the more dangerous; and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts principally in wiſdome and power, whether within us or without us; the wiſdom and power of fleſh in the things of God, which occaſions much pride and fleſhly exaltation above all that is called God: This is that deceivable
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62920:56"/> Antichriſt, that myſtery of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord will deſtroy by this ſpirit of his mouth, and this brightneſs of his coming: therefore let all wiſdome, pride and power of fleſh vale it ſelf to this excellent glory; for certainly its that which muſt be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in theſe later times. <hi>The day of the Lord of hoaſts ſhall be upon every one that is lifted up, and upon every one that is proud, and lofty, and he ſhall be brought low:</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proud thing within the Saints, and every proud and lifted up perſon among them, upon al the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that are high and lifted up, and upon al the Oaks of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> be they as tal as Cedars, as ſtrong as Oaks, yet the day of the Lord wil be upon them, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every high mountain, and upon al the hils that are lifted up, and upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very high tower, and upon every fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced wal, and upon al the ſhips of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiſh,</hi> and upon every pleaſant picture, and the loftineſs of man ſhal be bowed down, and the haughtineſs of man ſhal be made low, and the Lord alone ſhal be exalted in that day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. The day of the Lords power wil be upon al the wiſdome, pride, power, confidence,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62920:56"/> comfort and beauty of fleſh, and then the Lord alone ſhal be exalted in that day; this is the day of the Lords pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, we wil rejoyce and be glad in it, this wil miniſter true occaſion of joy to Saints, when they can ſay and ſing this ſong, <hi>The Lord God omnipotent reigneth.</hi> And thus this powerful law in the ſpirit wil appear in the ſubjecting al powers below, or contrary to it, unto it ſelfe, when al created powers whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this omnipotency, ſhal acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>That thou Lord God Almighty art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to receive glory, and honour, and majeſty, for thou only art worthy.</hi> Thus ſhal this power cauſe al other powers to bend the knee unto it, to ſubmit and fal down before it. Learne therefore to wait upon this powerful law to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh al your works for you, both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you and without you, to bring down al your fleſhly enemies, and then in concluſion ſhal you be able to ſee and ſay, that through the help of your God you have gone through an hoaſt, by the help of your God you have leaped over the wal.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The power of this Covenant and Law in the ſpirit appeares in that it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62920:57"/> thoſe in whom it is from falling; it endangers the ſoul to God; the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſtanding or falling is not left to the creature, but the power of God is become the Chriſtians power to uphold him; We preach Chriſt the wiſedome of God and the power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 24. Not onely wiſedome and power to convert, but to uphold and keep up the ſoule with the Almighty; hence this Covenant is called an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 40. And, ſaith the Lord, I will not turne from them to do them good, but I will put my feare in their hearts, and they ſhall not depart from me: this is the power of this ſpirituall law, it keeps ſouls perpetually with it ſelfe; ſo that as the Fathers love is an everlaſting love, ſo he makes with his people an everlaſting Covenant, that ſo their ſoules might live everlaſtingly in his everlaſting love. In a word, its this law of power which hath undertaken the effecting of all the Saints worke both within them and for them, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them through temptations, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and all oppoſitions both within and without, untill they come to be compleated in that Kingdome, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:62920:57"/> 42. 8, 9, 10. But thou <hi>Iſrael</hi> art my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>Jacob</hi> whom I have choſen, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> my friend: Believers are the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, the ſpirituall ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3. laſt. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. You whom I have taken from the ends of the earth, and called thee from the chief men thereof, and ſaid unto thee, thou art my ſervant, I have choſen thee and not caſt thee off; Feare them not, for I am with thee; be not diſmay'd, for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: A bleſſed word being ſpoken in the ſpirits of Gods <hi>Iſrael:</hi> how wil this raiſe ſoules above themſelves; worke them to a dependency upon him who is higher then themſelves? When the Lord ſpeakes this word with power, Feare not, I am thy God, I will uphold thee, I will helpe thee, &amp;c. What need ſuch a ſoule feare temptations, trials, enemies? This is that rock upon which Chriſt buildeth his Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it; a word of comfort for the weake Saints, they are not left to themſelves to ſtand or fall at their own power, but
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62920:58"/> they are carried along in the everlaſting armes of the Almighty; He carrieth his lambs in his boſome, he will not looſe one of his little ones, but will raiſe them up at the laſt day: See <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43. 1. 2, 3. But now thus ſaith the Lord that created thee, <hi>O Jacob,</hi> and he that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thee, <hi>O Iſrael,</hi> Feare not, for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by my name, thou art mine; When thou paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt through the waters I will be with thee, and through the rivers they ſhall not overflow thee; When thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee, for I am the Lord thy God, the holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thy Saviour; this is made good in the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, he undertakes for them, his power and ſtrength is to become theirs, he wil help them and uphold them, and carry them through fiery temptations and tryalls, through flouds of afflictions and tribulations: and thus through many a fiery tryall will he carry them to the Kingdome. Oh therefore looke to Jeſus the author and finiſher of your faith, looke to him who is your cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and workes all for you and all
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62920:58"/> all in you; it is his word to you, and likewiſe in you, <hi>Looke to me, and be yee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all the ends of the earth, for I am God, and there is none elſe, Iſaiah</hi> 45. 22. There is no power below or beſides God able to ſave you, able to uphold and keepe you, but he alone is able to keepe that which is committed unto him untill that day; and his power is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in his Saints.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The power of this Covenant, this law in the ſpirit enables to doe what it commands; it is not onely a law of light enlightening the minde, giving underſtanding to the ſimple; but it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on the ſoul in acting ſutable to the light communicated: hence it is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle could ſay, <hi>I can doe all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening me:</hi> And Chriſt, <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me you can doe nothing; It is he that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth both to will and to do of his good pleaſure; I worke,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>yet not I, but his grace in me, 1 Cor. 15. 10. I live, yet not I, but Christ lives in me, Gal.</hi> 2. 20. His power it is in you that deſtroyes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and fleſh; he it is in you that workes you up to a ſutable acting and walking with himſelfe; <hi>I,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>am dead to the law, that I might live</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:62920:59"/> 
                  <hi>unto God, Gal. 2. 19. Through the power of this law in the ſpirit am I dead to the law in the fleſh, that ſo in the ſame power I might live unto God:</hi> Thus Saints live in the power of this law, act to God in the light and power of God: an excellent thing to be knowne of Saints, where the power, the life of their lives lieth, <hi>Becauſe I live yee ſhall live alſo:</hi> Thus is Chriſt who is the Covenant become not onely the wiſedome of God, but the power of God in every one that believes: Thus this law in the ſpirit tranſcends all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawes beſides it ſelfe: the Law and Covenant of <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded, but gave no power to obey: hence it is the Lord complaines, <hi>Jer. 3. That they had broken the Covenant, though he was a husband unto them; but this is a Law, a Covenant not to be broken, becauſe it effects what it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> is called a <hi>weak Law, Rom. 8. 3. For what the Law could not doe in that it was weake through the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> This is a law of power, it doth that which the Covenant in the letter could not; that was a Covenant that could not give life, this is a law of life, a law of power in the ſpirits of Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:62920:59"/>
               <head>Chap. X. The power of the law in the fleſh.</head>
               <p>AS this Law, this Covenant in the ſpirit is a law of power, ſo there is a powerfull law in the fleſh likewiſe, though this law in the ſpirit over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powers it and ſubjects it to it ſelfe, where it is manifeſt in power.</p>
               <p>This law of power in the fleſh may be conſidered, either as it is more groſſe, or more refined.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it is more groſſe, powerfully working the mindes and actions of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men into a conformity unto it ſelfe; it carries on the naturall man to act all manner of unrighteouſneſſe, and that with greedineſſe: inſomuch that they thinke ſtrange of thoſe who run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot; thus it operates in naturall men.</p>
               <p>But 2. This ſame law of the fleſh workes with much power, many times even in the ſpirits of Chriſtians; this law of the fleſh rebelleth againſt the law of the minde, and lendeth captive
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62920:60"/> to the law of ſinne in the members; how can Saints experience this truth? Many times though the inner man be upright, and as they are borne of God, they ſinne not, yet what temptations, what workings of fleſh appeares within them? which occaſions blackneſſe and darkneſſe many times, the appearance of fleſh in a way of power, which ſeemes to ſtoppe the current of the ſoules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent communion, and leaves it under a waiting condition for deliverance.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Is this law in the fleſh too strange and powerfull for that in the ſpirit, when it ſeemes thus to prevaile in its rebelling againſt that holy law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Its not too ſtrong for it, but wiſedome gives way to this rebelling law, that it may act its part, that ſo the ſoule may ſee it ſelfe what it is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo may the more prize grace, and the more earneſtly waite for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and likewiſe for the keeping of the ſoule in a humble waiting, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency upon this Almighty power; therefore he ſends a pricke in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buffet, leſt there ſhould be an exaltation above meaſure, as experience teacheth us, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62920:60"/> fleſh is ready to take advantage, and that from ſpirituall diſcoveries.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This law in the fleſh worketh in a more refined and pure, though in a more deceivable way; not onely in working ſoules with violence and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe in a way of ſinne, but likewiſe worke ſoules when they come to ſee their ſinne into a fleſhly righteouſneſſe; ſo that the ſoule being ignorant of the righteouſneſſe of God, it goes about to eſtabliſh its owne righteouſneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 3. And ſo it workes the ſoule into a fleſhly boaſting, and a fleſhly glorying in fleſhly and carnall excellencies, and that with as much violence as into a way of ſinne and prophaneneſſe, unleſſe the power of this ſpirituall law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; then its true the ſoule is content with joy to ſuffer the loſſe of all, and and to account all things but dung and droſſe that it may winne Chriſt, and be found in him; then its content not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuffer the loſſe of this law in the fleſh in the groſſer conſideration, but in the moſt refined conſideration; then it can ſay, <hi>What things were gaine to me thoſe I counted loſſe for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:62920:61"/>
               <head>Chap. XI. The glory of this law in the ſpirit.</head>
               <p>THis Covenant in the ſpirit is a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Covenant; when Chriſt comes, he comes with power and much glory; this law rules in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where there is power and much glory. The glory of this Covenant appeares not onely in all thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned particulars, as its a law of light, liberty, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, power, &amp;c. which muſt needs produce much glory where all thoſe excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies met together in one ſoule, and all are glorious, glorious light, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe, and power, it muſt needs be glorious, when made partaker of the light, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, power and glory of the glorious God.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, for illuſtrating of this glorious law, I might minde how it,</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62920:61"/>
               <p n="1">1. Intereſts the ſoule in whom it is into a neare relation to the Father, not onely of ſon, and of heire, but likewiſe the relation of Wife, of Spouſe, and ſo is married to the Almighty eternally; this is a name better then that of ſons and daughters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This glorious law makes forth many glorious diſcoveries and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the hearts of Chriſtians, <hi>Such as eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe things that he hath prepared for them that love him, but he hath revealed it to, or in us by his ſpirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 9, 10. Oh thoſe ſweet diſcoveries God oft makes in the ſpirits of his, that they can ſay ſweetly to their ſoules after a blacke and darke day, <hi>Returne to thy reſt, O my ſoule, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee:</hi> Thus are they let ſee into that glorious myſtery of love which paſſeth knowledge.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As it diſcovers glory, ſo it works a glorious minde, a deſire in the minde to be compleated in this glory; not out of ſelfe-love (as moſt doe deſire heaven that they might avoid hel) but for glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſake its ſelfe it beholds its beauty,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62920:62"/> its ſweetneſſe, its purity, its perfection, and ſo the ſoule is overcome with it; nothing in the world is to be compared to it: and hence it is that Saints have ſuch noble, heroick ſpirits, looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, ſlighting all things below as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, all riches and creature-excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and glories is but graſſe, but droſſe unto it; this is the nature of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious law, it fils the ſoule with ſo much glory where it is, that the deſire is taken up with it, becauſe it out-glories all other glories in the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As it is an out-glorying glory, and ſo drawes the deſire of the minde unto it, ſo it is likewiſe a transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, changing glory, it never leaves ſoules in whom it is til it compleates them in al the glory ſet before them, it workes up ſoules more and more to it ſelfe untill it hath perfected them in the glory of the Father; <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy maſter:</hi> Hence it was <hi>Paul</hi> being poſſeſt with this truth, expecting this compleating in glory, preſſes on to the marke of the price of the high calling
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62920:62"/> ſet before him; and was able to ſay, <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, from henceforth is laid up for me a crowne of glory, which the Lord the righteous Judge hath laid up for me, and not for me onely, but for all thoſe who looke for his appearing.</hi> Oh therefore my deare brethren in the unity of this ſpirit looke and waite for this day of God, the glorious appearing of the great God, becauſe when he ſhall appear, you ſhall appeare with him in glory, and you never enjoy the end of your faith until you come into the perfection of this glorious ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:62920:63"/>
               <head>Chap. XII. The law in the ſpirit a law of peace.</head>
               <p>THere is a falſe and fleſhly joy and glory likewiſe which ariſes from the law in the fleſh; and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
               <p>1. When creatures glory in ſin and prophaneneſſe, and ungodlineſſe; ſuch a glorying is not good, it will prove their ſhame.</p>
               <p>Or, 2. When men glory in the world, in their profits, pleaſures and honours; this glorying likewiſe is after the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Or elſe, 3. When men glory in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal priviledges, as they call them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are indeed but deluſions, as ordinances, formes, performances, &amp;c. This likewiſe is but a fleſhly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, and that which Chriſt fore-told, <hi>Mat. 7. 22. Luk.</hi> 13. 26, 27. and the Apoſtle rejected, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Or elſe, 4. When men are gotten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62920:63"/> ſuch a notion as that now al is good, every worke of the fleſh, and deed of darkeneſſe is now juſtifiable, and they glory in it, why al theſe are but fleſhly gloryings: And to ſuch I ſay, Glory not, lie not againſt the truth, for a day is coming when al fleſh ſhal vale it ſelfe unto this excellent glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and al other glories ſhal periſh as graſſe, as dung upon the earth, and if mercy prevent not, al theſe gloryings wil prove your ſhame, <hi>Becauſe you have rejoyced in lying vanities; you have made lies your refuge, and covered your ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der falſhood.</hi> And to you I ſay, who have taſted how gracious, how pure, how glorious the Lord is; <hi>Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome, nor the rich man in his riches, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength: but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he knows the Lord:</hi> and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him, <hi>That the Lord is his portion,</hi> his relation to him, that he is his ſon, his delight, that he is heir with Chriſt to the ſame inheritance to the ſame glory; and this is a glory wil out glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry al fleſhly gloryings, in which men of the earth are taken up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62920:64"/> Or elſe 5. when this man of ſin gets higher in filling the fancy with high apprehenſions and glorious imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſeeming revelations to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement in the creatures apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it thinks certainly its the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God, but the trial is, it ends al in fleſh, fils the ſoule with pride and ſelfe-exaltations, and is but <hi>like unto new wine put into old bottles,</hi> that burſt them al to peeces, and by this meanes the evil one takes an advantage to blow them up root and branch, and ſo to put an end to that which ſeemed to be in them, whereas the diſcoveries of the ſpiritual law makes ſoules in whom it is, the more humble, the more ſpiritual, the more conformable to it ſelfe: and the more this glorious law appeares the more it changes the ſoule into its owne glory, the more is fleſh and fleſhly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſubdued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:62920:64"/>
               <head>Chap. XIII. It is likewiſe a Law of peace.</head>
               <p>I Shal adde two or three particulars further in the diſcovery of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in the ſpirit: And</p>
               <p>Firſt, Its a Covenant, a Law of peace: Its not onely a law of grace and love, but its likewiſe a law of peace: hence its called in Scripture, a Covenant of peace, <hi>Ezek. 37. 26. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over I will make a covenant of peace with them, and it ſhall be an everlaſting covenant, &amp;c.</hi> This everlaſting Covenant of grace, is a Covenant of peace in the ſpirits of Saints, he is our peace, <hi>who hath broken down that middle wall of partition between us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 14. This Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of peace may be conſidered, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it workes the ſoule into a peace and unity with the Father, that now the ſoul who was once afarre off, is made neare through the bloud of this Covenant, <hi>and ſo being juſtified by faith</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:62920:65"/> 
                  <hi>we have peace with God through our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt:</hi> and the kingdome of God within the Saints is a kingdome of righteouſneſſe, peace and joy. This is that the Apoſtle ſo often mindes in his Epiſtles, <hi>Grace, mercy and peace from God our Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is that peace of God which paſſeth al underſtanding, of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and fleſh, this is that peace which produceth joy which is unſpeakable and full of glory: Now the ſoule being in a Covenant of peace can goe boldly to the throne of grace, there to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip with the God and Father of peace, being made through grace a ſon of peace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This law of peace works the ſoul into a peace with all creatures, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it with a diſpoſition of peace and love: He is now at emnity with none, ready to doe good to all, to pray for enemies, and thoſe who oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being poſſeſt with that law in the ſpirit, which is pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruites, <hi>James</hi> 3. 17, 18. without partiality, without hypocriſie, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe is ſowne in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62920:65"/> peace, in them who love peace: This diſpoſition is planted in them, as much as in them lieth, to live peaceable with al men. Thus are Saints not onely a people of grace, but a people of peace; the fruit of righteouſnes being ſown in peace in them, they recompence not evil for evil, but overcom evil with goodnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This law of peace affords peace and quietneſſe to the ſoul in al conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, under al trials and temptations, when others hearts ſhal fail them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things which ſhal come upon the face of the earth, <hi>They ſhall lift up their heads with joy, being poſſeſt with peace, knowing that their redemption and deliverance draweth near.</hi> Thus are Saints quieted in their ſpirits through this ſpirit of peace, <hi>Iſa. 32. 17, 18, 19. And the worke of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall be peace, and the effect of righteouſneſſe ſhall be quietneſſe, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for ever, And my people ſhall dwell in peaceable habitations, and in ſure dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and in quiet resting places: When it ſhall hail, coming downe upon the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and the City ſhall be low in a low place.</hi> Here is a glorious Covenant of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62920:66"/> peace and quiet, and this ſhall be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted when the ſpirit is poured forth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. which wil produce ſuch ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, quiet and peace in Chriſtians and that when the City is low in a low place, and hail comes down upon the foreſt, that is earthy creatures and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites ſhall be filled with trouble, perplexity, and amazement, then ſhal Saints live in reſt, and quiet peace ſhal come, they ſhall reſt ſecure, nothing ſhall make them afraid; Bleſſed are they which ſow beſide al waters in this water of life, whoſe effect will be in ſuch a ſoule quietneſſe, and peace for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:62920:66"/>
               <head>Chap. XIV. Of the Law of Love.</head>
               <p>2. THis law in the ſpirit, as its a law of peace, ſo its likewiſe a law of love, its the royal law of love, love being the great command, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient command, commanded not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the letter, but in the ſpirit like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: where this law is in power, this is manifeſt; firſt to God, God being love drawes love from ſoules: its true hee workes it firſt in them, and then being poſſeſt with love they cannot but love; We love God becauſe he loved us firſt, and this love being ſhed abroad in the heart, by this ſpirit wee love him, wee love him moſt, we love him beſt; he hath the heart, the ſoul, and its marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him; all other lovers being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in compariſon of him.</p>
               <p>2. This ſpirit of love and grace pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth love to the Saints in whom the image of God, holines and true righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes appears: take this as an undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truth, That where the love of God
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62920:67"/> is ſhed abroad by the ſpirit, there will be a ſweet harmony in thoſe ſoules, a ſweet agreement; Love as brethren, being al ſonnes related to one Father, al poſſeſt with one ſpirit, which it a ſpirit of unity, al heirs to one inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to one Crowne, to one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, al made partaker of the ſame divine nature, which is love: there is no one thing wherein the viſibility of a Saint more appeares then in love; for love is of God, and every one who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth is born of God, and knoweth God; hee that loveth not knoweth not God, for God is love, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 7, 8. and he that loveth not his brother, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nor loveth God.</p>
               <p>3. This ſpirit of love produceth love in Saints to al: it makes thoſe in whom it is like unto their Father who is good unto al, and his tender mercy is over al his workes, as much as in them lieth, they doe good to al, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe who are of the houſhold of faith. In a word, this ſpirit takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that ſelfiſh diſpoſition of nature in ſeeking it ſelf, and cauſeth the ſoule in whom it is not to ſeeke alone its owne but others good; it workes out that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62920:67"/> peeviſh, perverſe and envious diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and fils the ſoul with the ſpirit of love, and that not feigned in ſhew, but in deed and in truth, ready with a real minde at al times to doe good to any man, to any creature, that is capable of receiving good. Thus (my deare Friends) as God is love, ſo thoſe who dwel in God, dwel in love; and its from the fleſh, and not from the ſpirit that thoſe diviſions, backbitings and reproachings flow, who cal themſelves by the name of Chriſtians. This I muſt tel you, that where the ſoul is poſſeſt with love and grace from the Father it produceth love and grace ſutable to ſuch an injoyment; for grace and love in God being ſhed abroad in us, works grace and love in us, love to God, to Saints, to al men, and hee that hath not this grace, this love in him, how dwelleth the love of God in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:62920:68"/>
               <head>Chap. XV. Its a Law of Edification.</head>
               <p>3. THis law in the ſpirit its like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a law of edification: it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that exhortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be done to edification:</hi> It is this law of grace which ſeaſons the ſoul with grace, &amp; the words and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations with ſalt, that it may miniſter grace to the hearers; have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In a word, it delivers ſoules from earthlineſſe, vanity and folly, from carnal and unprofitable diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and that word of Chriſt is made good in them, <hi>John 7. 38. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in me out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living waters.</hi> And this hee ſpake of the ſpirit, that he would give, and this ſpirit, that he would give, and this ſpirit giveth ſeveral gifts, worketh ſeveral operations, but its given to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to profit withall.</p>
               <p>How might this diſcover then firſt the fleſhlineſſe of thoſe who pretend to be Chriſtians, and yet manifeſt nothing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62920:68"/> but fleſh; vanity and unprofitableneſſe in their diſcourſes and communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, full of earth and fleſh, but emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heavenlineſſe and ſpirit.</p>
               <p>2. This diſcovers the fleſhlineſſe of thoſe, pretending ſuch Chriſtianity, yet delight in vanity, I had almoſt ſaid, ſlight, if not ſcorne any ſpiritual or heavenly communication, which tends to edification: and indeed this law of love and edification is much wanting; And therfore my exhortation to al you who have taſted how gracious the Lord is, to waite upon him for a more ful pouring forth of this ſpirit of peace, love and edification, that ſo you may declare your ſelves to be a people of peace and love; that you may become a bleſſing, a comfort each to other; that the peace and love of God ſhining in you, and through you, may ſo conform you to it ſelf, and ſo gather you up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its owne nature, that you may ſhine forth as a people poſſeſt indeed with love, that is, may be made knowne to al men, that you are indeed the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of a heavenly Father, not of this world, being born from above, not of mortal, but of immortal ſeed, which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62920:69"/> ſhal endure for ever; ſo ſhal you be to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, <hi>who hath called you to an immortall crowne, an eternal kingdome and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which never ſhall have an end.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 9. lin. 1. for in righteous, reade inlightens. p. 16. l. 15. for eyes r. dies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62920:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
